<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached the first in Richmond Church, August 17. 1690. on the most happy accession of Their Majesties, King William and Queen Mary to the Crown. The second in Mortlake Chuch in Surrey March 3. 1694. on the death of our late most gracious soveraign lady the Queen, of blessed memory. The third in Mortlake Church, April 16. 1696. being the day of Thanksgiving unto Almighty God, for discovering and disappointing the horrid and barbarous conspiracy to assassinate His most gracious Majesty's royal person: and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion, intended by the French. By Christopher Johnson, M.A. and school-master of Richmond in Surrey. Printed to prevent mistakes concerning the author.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Christopher, b. 1657 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J770BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1950:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached the first in Richmond Church, August 17. 1690. on the most happy accession of Their Majesties, King William and Queen Mary to the Crown. The second in Mortlake Chuch in Surrey March 3. 1694. on the death of our late most gracious soveraign lady the Queen, of blessed memory. The third in Mortlake Church, April 16. 1696. being the day of Thanksgiving unto Almighty God, for discovering and disappointing the horrid and barbarous conspiracy to assassinate His most gracious Majesty's royal person: and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion, intended by the French. By Christopher Johnson, M.A. and school-master of Richmond in Surrey. Printed to prevent mistakes concerning the author.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Christopher, b. 1657 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Samuel Buckley, at the Dolphin over against St. Dunstan's Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The deliverance of God's Church. Sermon I", "The glory departed. Sermon II", and "The living Lord, a rock of salvation. Sermon II" have divisional title pages; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32727:1"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS PREACHED The Firſt in <hi>Richmond</hi> Church, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 17. 1690. On the Moſt Happy Acceſſion of Their Majeſties, KING <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and QUEEN <hi>MARY</hi> to the Crown.</p>
            <p>The Second in <hi>Mortlake</hi> Church in <hi>Surrey, March</hi> 3. 1694. On the Death of Our Late Moſt Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lady the QUEEN, of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>The Third in <hi>Mortlake</hi> Church, <hi>April</hi> 16. 1696. Being the Day of Thankſgiving unto Almighty God, for Diſcovering and Diſappointing the Horrid and Barbarous Conſpiracy to Aſſaſſinate His Moſt Gracious Majeſty's Royal Perſon: And for Delivering this Kingdom from an Invaſion, intended by the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>CHRISTOPHER JOHNSON,</hi> M. A. and School-maſter of <hi>Richmond</hi> in <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RREY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed to prevent Miſtakes concerning the Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Buckley,</hi> at the <hi>Dolphin</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32727:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32727:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Reaſon of Printing theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons is this: Mr. <hi>Abiel Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet,</hi> the late Minister of <hi>Richmond</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> having written, and ſuffer'd to be diſperſed, ſome Scandalous and Ill No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, concerning the Preſent Most Happy Government; for which he is Deprived of his <hi>Cure;</hi> ſome Perſons by Mistake did apprehend the <hi>Author</hi> of theſe Sermons, being a Clergy-man, and living in <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> to be the ſaid Minister thereof, and the Author of thoſe Ill Notions. To obviate which, and rectifie the Errour; and to prevent for the future any the like
<pb facs="tcp:32727:3"/>Miſrepreſentations of this Author; He thought it convenient to make the following Sermons publick.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. l. 9. <hi>calamnities</hi> r. <hi>calamities.</hi> p. 12. l. 2. <hi>are the cauſe,</hi> r. <hi>are often the cauſe.</hi> l. 29. <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>on.</hi> p. 13. l. 24. <hi>flames,</hi> r. <hi>a flame.</hi> p. 14. l. 15. <hi>Diocleſian's,</hi> r. <hi>Diocletian's.</hi> l. 17. <hi>almoſt,</hi> r. <hi>for almoſt.</hi> p. 18. l. 1. <hi>Nay,</hi> r. <hi>Yea,</hi> l. 10. <hi>a,</hi> r. <hi>the.</hi> p. 21. l. 26. the firſt <hi>of,</hi> r. <hi>for.</hi> p. 22. l. 27. after <hi>Faith</hi> put? l. the laſt, <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>as appears by.</hi> p. 23. l. 37. <hi>born by,</hi> r. <hi>born of.</hi> p. 25. l. 18. <hi>into his place,</hi> r. <hi>unto his place.</hi> p. 30. l. 7, and 8. r. <hi>threatned their total deſtruction, and in part at leaſt wrought it.</hi> p. 31. l. 17. <hi>Her Houſhold,</hi> r. <hi>the ways of her Houſhold.</hi> l. 26. <hi>which,</hi> r. <hi>as.</hi> p. 48. l. 1. <hi>Propoſition,</hi> r. <hi>Particular.</hi> Where you find <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice,</hi> you may read <hi>rejoyce.</hi> And if there be any more <hi>Errata</hi>'s over looked, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is deſired to Correct them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:3"/>
                  <p>The Deliverance of GOD's Church.</p>
                  <p>SERMON I. Preached in <hi>Richmond</hi> Church in <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RREY, Auguſt</hi> the 17th, 1690.</p>
                  <p>On the Happy Acceſſion of their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> III. and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> II. to the Crown.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:4"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32727:4"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>NUMB. xxiii. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Surely there is no Enchantment againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> neither is there any Divination against <hi>Iſrael:</hi> —</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>AS God hath a Church Triumphant in Heaven; pure and undefiled, clean from all Sin, and free from all Sorrow; Glorious without Spot, and Joyful without the allay of but one Moments Affliction; out of all danger of any Enemy, and Eternally bleſt with Crowns and Palms of Victory: So hath he a Church Militant on Earth, his Delight, and of him greatly Beloved; Holy, Catholick or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, full of good Works, but yet not perfect; ſome True, and though their Lights ſhine; in one ſence, inviſible Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, becauſe none knows the Heart of a Man; yet theſe not without Sin, though their Errours and Failings are pardonable, and ſhall be forgiven them: Others viſible Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers only, and Hypocrites, who make a bare outward ſhew in the World, and whoſe Sins ſhall not be remitted unto them, without the ſpecial Grace of Repentance and Amendment, whereby a timely Converſion may, through the Merits of Chriſt, obtain Salvation. But the Church of God on Earth, not being perfect, is ſubject to Sufferings: Her own Sins arm, and make her Enemies powerful againſt her: Her Shame eclipſeth her Glory, and cauſeth Sorrows, which often exceed her Joys: whilſt always Fighting, ſhe is Victorious but in part, by reaſon of <hi>Sin, that doth ſo eaſily beſet her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet her Infirmities do not annul God's Favours towards her; but when the Reins are let looſe, and Provocations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to a great height, Divine Juſtice is concern'd in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of it ſelf, to unſheath the Sword, and brandiſh it at leaſt, if not ſtrike, for the Amendment of thoſe, who will be healed; and for the Terrour and Aſtoniſhment, if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Confuſion, of obſtinate Offenders. Neither is Juſtice alone
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32727:5"/>here, but Love and Mercy are Concomitant therewith, becauſe the Deſign of God in the whole is, that all may work together for the good of that Myſtical Body, of which Chriſt is the Head: and therefore it is, that when a Lenitive will not Cure, he applies a Corroſive Plaiſter to the Sore. For various have been the Methods of the Almighty, to keep his People in his Favour, and at one with him.</p>
                  <p>And not this only, but, what I am chiefly to inſiſt upon, God hath in a moſt Eminent Manner, upon all Occaſions, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Cauſe of his Church, for the Preſervation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, againſt all her Foes, in the Patriarchal and Jewiſh, as well as Chriſtian Oeconomy and Government; for ſuch, we read, have been in Ancient time (beſides what <hi>our Fathers have told us,</hi> and we next after them do now know, and hope further to ſee) the Mighty Deliverances of God's People, as declare them to be the only Immediate Care of his Watchful, and All-ſeeing Eyes of Providence, for whom Omnipotence it ſelf hath, and doth ſtretch forth its Mighty Arm to work Wonders: Which great things very much need required to be done, all along from the beginning of the World unto this Day, for the Salvation of God's Church. For in the Infancy thereof, when there were only two, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> to gather together in God's Name to Adore him, and perform their Duties of Piety and Religion, even then the grand Enemy of Mankind ſet to work for their Deſtruction, by Helliſh Enchantments, added unto the ſubtilty of that Serpent, which, though not the Devil himſelf in that form, yet at leaſt, was poſſeſt with, and ſpake by him; and ſo by the Voice and Language of Satan, dreſt up with many Artifices of pleaſing words, the Temptation became ſo ſtrong, that the Woman, ſoon beguiled thereby, caught at the deadly Bait, and <hi>did eat, and gave alſo unto her Husband, and be did eat:</hi> And then ſo far, even in Paradiſe it ſelf, Satan accompliſhed his Deſign, and, <hi>as Fiſhes that are taken in an evil Net, and as Birds that are caught in the Snare, ſo were</hi> they both <hi>ſnared in an evil time,</hi> by that Evil One, the Tempter.</p>
                  <p>But although our Firſt Parents had the Misfortune to fall from ſuch an high and lofty Sphere of Primitive Purity, to which they, or their Poſterity might never think to aſcend again in this World; yet was not Satan able to purſue, and gain a compleat Victory over them, becauſe God in Mercy reinforced
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32727:5"/>them with ſuch ſtrength, by virtue of his Promiſe, that <hi>the Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpent's Head;</hi> according to the Covenant of Grace, wherein it was promiſed, that the Meſſias ſhould come into the World to Redeem Mankind, and to Deſtroy the Works of the Devil: Whereby a poſſibility of regaining what we have loſt, yea, and a better Paradice too, is left unto us.</p>
                  <p>And now the Devil being thus fruſtrated of his prime intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miſchief, and Cruel Invention againſt Man, and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged therefore; it is his Property ever ſince to go about like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he may devour, endeavouring to Circumſcribe Hell and Earth in one Circle, and to unite the Forces of both for the Deſtruction of God's Church; to raiſe all ſorts of Deviliſh Engines to hatter her, and to let no Stratagem eſcape him, that the Malice and Fury of Devils and Wicked Men can invent. But yet, neither the Sword, nor the Bow, the Horſe, nor his Rider, ſhall prevail againſt her in the Day of Battel; not whole Legions of Devils, nor the Counſels and Purpoſes of Hell. No Sorcerer or Magician ſhall come to Curſe or Deſie God's Holy Church, but at laſt, after all ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Trials and Devices againſt her, ſhall be forced, with a Bleſſing in his Mouth, inſtead of a Curſe, to declare, <hi>Surely there is no Enchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were the words of <hi>Balaam,</hi> a great Sorcerer in the Eaſtern Country, whom <hi>Balak</hi> King of <hi>Moab</hi> invited, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come, and Curſe <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to Defie <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the peculiar People and Church of God in thoſe Days; and who Travelling to the <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> had Encamped in the Plains of <hi>Moab,</hi> whereupon <hi>Balak</hi> was almoſt at his Wits end, ſeeing them vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly numerous, and knowing that lately, before them, <hi>Sihon</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and <hi>Og</hi> King of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> two of his greateſt Neighbouring Princes, had fallen: But chiefly he was afraid of them, becauſe ſenſible of their Strength and Safety by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Almighty, which he hoped to withdraw from them by the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Balaam:</hi> who yet was not able in the leaſt to effect that wicked Deſire, by all his Magick Arts and Sorceries, nor by many Altars, and Bullocks, and Rams offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereon, for that purpoſe: But after much ado, and many Devices, he found himſelf under a conſtraint to Bleſs them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32727:6"/>whether he would or no, and to ſpeak the preſent Thoughts of his Mind thus, <hi>Surely there is no Enchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>In which words there is a Synonymie, that makes both parts of my Text to ſignifie one and the ſame thing; upon which ſome have gloſſed thus, That there was no ſuch thing as Sorcery or Enchantments, and ſuch like evil Arts pleaſing unto, or in uſe among the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by reaſon of the interdiction of the Law of God to the contrary; and this they take from thoſe Tranſlations, that render the Text by the Particle <hi>in,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>againſt,</hi> and then the Text runs thus, <hi>Surely there is no Enchantment in</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination in</hi> Iſrael. Others, by reading the words according to the more natural or genuin Sence, as we have Tranſlated them, <hi>Surely there is no Enchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael, paraphraſe on them in this more currant Stile, that no Deviliſh Art can hurt the People of God: and ſo there is no effectual deviſing Evil againſt them, though by Witchcraft it ſelf, nor any obſerving or preſaging Evil Fortune unto them, by all the Black Art of Hell. And then from this Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on flows this Infallible Propoſition.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That the Church of God ſhall always ſtand firm againſt the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Fury of all her Enemies.</hi> To which I ſhall ſubjoin, that,</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>She hath been, and ſhall be enabled, ſo to abide in Safety, by the Protection, and good Providence of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The Church of God ſhall always ſtand firm againſt the Oppoſition and Fury of all her Enemies.</hi> For by our Bleſſed Saviour's words, we underſtand that <hi>ſhe is Built upon a Rock,</hi> and that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt her.</hi> All the Powers of Darkneſs ſhall not undermine her Foundations, and no Storms or Aſſaults ſhall prevail for her Deſtruction: and if <hi>the Heathen,</hi> even all her Enemies ſhould <hi>rage againſt her,</hi> they ſhall only <hi>imagine a vain thing;</hi> though <hi>the Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take Counſel together,</hi> how to pull her down, and lay her Honour in the Duſt; how to make our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> an heap of Stones, ſo that <hi>Zion</hi> ſhould be had no more in remembrance, that her Captivity ſhould never return any more: Though they ſhould endeavour this with all the Policy, and Power, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32727:6"/>Wit of Man; yet let them know in the words of the Pſalmiſt, That <hi>he that ſitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion;</hi> that <hi>then he ſhall ſpeak unto them in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure,</hi> Pſal. 2.4, 5.</p>
                  <p>Where God is repreſented as ſitting aloft in the Heavens, and as if from thence he were looking down upon the Children of Men, marking their Follies, in thoſe ridiculous and vain At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, they ſo eagerly purſue, with all their might againſt his Church; and as if this did, after the manner of Men, cauſe laughter in him; and ſo firſt of all he did only mock at and deride them: But then at laſt ſeeing them continue to work Wickedneſs, he ſpeaks unto them, and that in his Anger too. He begins to be Jealous for his People, and the Thunder of his Voice is heard, as well as that of his Power is felt, as it appears by theſe words, <hi>and</hi> he ſhall <hi>vex them in his ſore Diſpleaſure:</hi> which is done, when he turns the <hi>Counſel</hi> of the greateſt <hi>Achitophels</hi> into <hi>Fooliſhneſs,</hi> and defeats all their Purpoſes; when he ſends out the <hi>Fingers of a Man's Hand</hi> writing <hi>upon the Plaiſter of the Wall,</hi> MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN; <hi>God hath numbred thy Kingdom, and finiſhed it. Thou art weighed in the Balances, and art found wanting, Thy Kingdom is divided, and given to</hi> Others.</p>
                  <p>And then God vexeth the Enemies of his Church, when, as he did to <hi>Gideon,</hi> he ſends his Angel unto ſome great Perſon, with this Salutation, <hi>The Lord is with thee, thou mighty Man of Valour;</hi> or by ſome ſecret Inſtinct moves him, and Seals his Commiſſion with full Power and Authority to go forth for the Deliverance of his People, and is always with him: So that if he paſſes over the great Deep, God either ſtilleth the raging of the Sea, or elſe ſuffereth not the Floods, and toſſing Waves thereof, to come near him. And if in the Field, and in the Battel, and the Engines of Deſtruction are planted againſt, and let fly at him, yet the very Meſſenger of Death ſent from thoſe Inſtruments of Cruelty very near him, ſhall have no power over his Life: but that God who ſent him, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him, and give him Victory and Honour, againſt all the Plots and Contrivances of his Enemies, though they are in Conjunction with the Black Society of all the Infernal Regions: for what Evil they Invent, God Diſappoints, that they may underſtand what they would not, The words of the Wiſe Man, Prov. 19.21. <hi>There are many Devices in a Man's Heart; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32727:7"/>the Counſel of the Lord, that ſhall ſtand.</hi> And ſo long as that ſtands, his Church ſhall ſtand firm. And if at any time ſhe groans, by reaſon of the Fury and Oppreſſions of her Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, he will hear her Cry, and help her. She ſhall <hi>ſtand ſtill, and ſee the Salvation of the Lord,</hi> which he will ſhew unto her. She ſhall be aſſured, that he will <hi>deliver her in Six Troubles, yea, in Seven:</hi> and then ſhall ſhe reſt ſatisfied, that although <hi>many are the Troubles of the Righteous, yet the Lord delivereth them out of them all,</hi> when ſhe hath ſeen ſo much of the Goodneſs of the Lord in the Land of the Living. But if at any time, her Sins, which (to be ſure) are frequently the ſad and woful Cauſe of her Sorrows (for they merit Puniſhments) do give her Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries both time and power to inſult over her, and her Faith and Hope begin to fail, ſo that ſhe becomes dubious, and miſtruſts the veracity of that Promiſe, made in particular to <hi>Joſhua;</hi> but, by the <hi>Author</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> applied unto all the Faithful, as a general and ſtanding Rule of Truſt and Confidence in God's Mercy and Protection, which is this, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee, Heb.</hi> 13.5. In ſuch Affliction and Anxiety of Mind, let her amend, and not deſpair of God's Love and Mercy. And if at the firſt appearance of help, and notice of God's eſpecial Preſence with her, after many Evils of Puniſhment from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſhe ſhould deſpond; like <hi>Gideon,</hi> when almoſt in Deſpair, an Angel appear'd unto him, with this Sign in his Mouth, from the Lord, of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Deliverance from the Oppreſſion of <hi>Midian, the Lord is with thee;</hi> who, with a ſort of diffidence of the Divine Meſſage, return'd this Anſwer to the Angel's Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, as it were with Sorrow in his Heart; <hi>Oh my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us? And where be all his Miracles, which our Fathers told us of, ſaying, Did not the Lord bring us up from</hi> Egypt? <hi>But now the Lord bath forſaken us, and delivered us into the Hands of the</hi> Midianites, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.13.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall endeavour preſently to give Comfort and ſome Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, Should the Church and People of God, in Times of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, anſwer after the ſame manner, If the Lord be with us, why doth the Enemy rejoice, and the Adverſary triumph over us? If it be an Infallible Aphoriſm, that his Church ſhall ſtand always firm, againſt the Oppoſition and Fury of all her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; how is it that from the beginning of the World unto this Day, Perſecution hath been a large ſhare of her Portion? Her
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32727:7"/>Tears have been often poured into <hi>the Cup of trembling,</hi> to add the greater Bitterneſs unto every drop, ſhe hath been forced to drink; and the Bread of Sorrow hath been her daily Food. Her Children have been ſtoned, ſawn aſunder, tempted, ſlain with the Sword, and a Thouſand ſorts of Deaths and Tortures have been inflicted upon them; ſo that no Sorrow was ever like unto her Sorrow. At one time Righteous <hi>Abel</hi> was Murder'd by his own Impious Brother <hi>Cain;</hi> here the Bloody Tragedy began, and ſucceſſively was acted on, with various Troubles and Torments unto the People of God, even to the Days of holy <hi>Elijah:</hi> who alſo then found himſelf grievouſly perſecuted by wicked <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and that ſo ſharply, that he preferred Death before Life, when he requeſted for himſelf that he might Die, and ſaid, <hi>It is enough now, O Lord, take away my Life,</hi> 1 King. 19.4.</p>
                  <p>And twice in the ſame Chapter, we find him ſadly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of thoſe who had deſerted the true Worſhip of God, for that which was falſe and idolatrous, and did perſecute thoſe who would not depart with them, from ſerving the Living and True God; as theſe words of that holy Man do infer, <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have forſaken thy Covenant, thrown down thine Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and ſlain thy Prophets with the Sword; and I, even I only am left, and they ſeek my Life to take it away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So ſharp and general, it ſeems, was the Perſecution, that <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah</hi> thought, that all the Prophets, and Faithful People of God, were quite ſwept away thereby; for he had ſome time ſince fled for his own Life; and, as the words ſeem to intimate, when he came again, no true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was to be ſeen, or did not dare to ſhew his Face, and venture to ſtand before the heat and fury of <hi>Jezebel</hi>'s inveterate Malice and Hatred to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of True Religion.</p>
                  <p>But yet, God be thanked, for the Comfort of good <hi>Elijah,</hi> Wickedneſs had not ſate ſo long in the place of Judgment and Righteouſneſs, to Triumph ſo far, as to bring the Church in thoſe Days to ſo low an Ebb, as to have the Tears of but one true Member only to run down for her, and by the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of whoſe Life, ſhe ſhould have been quite cut off: For in the 18th Verſe of the aforecited Chapter, we find the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting <hi>Elijah</hi> thus, with a goodly number of truly Religious Perſons ſtill remaining, <hi>Yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I have left me Seven Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32727:8"/>in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>all the Knees, which have not bowed unto</hi> Baal, <hi>and every Mouth, which hath not kiſſed him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now further may we find the Church clad in Sackcloth, with Duſt and Aſhes upon her Head, mourning in her Travail, and bringing forth Children with great Lamentation, weeping and wailing; for that, reckoning from the Days of <hi>Elijah</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, her Afflictions were from time to time renewed. Once a whole Seventy Years Captivity in a ſtrange Land, beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wars and Troubles from the Enemy, before and after that, unto the time that <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Prince, the Glory and Head of the Church came, when alſo <hi>He was cut off,</hi> not for himſelf, but for the Tranſgreſſion of his People: This was moſt Amazing, and full of Wo, the cutting off of Members was not enough, but the Head muſt ſuffer as much too. This cauſed the Sun, that great Luminary, to put on mourning Apparel of the deepeſt Dye, a black and thick Darkneſs. It forced the Earth into a Convulſion, to ſhake and tremble, and the Temple to rend its Vail in twain. Then did Nature ſuffer a Diſſolution for a time; and needs muſt the whole Creation groan, and be in pain, when Chriſt himſelf cried out with a loud and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Voice, and ſuffer'd the deepeſt pangs of Body and Soul.</p>
                  <p>This was the <hi>Child of God,</hi> and Heir of all things, that pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out his Soul unto Death, whom the great Red Dragon, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Revelations of St. <hi>John,</hi> thought wholly to devour; but yet did he revive on the Third Day, and was afterwards caught up unto God: I mean, he aſcended into Heaven, where he Reigns King and Head of the Church, in Triumph over all his Enemies.</p>
                  <p>And now the great Red Dragon, that Old Serpent, called the Devil and Satan, being caſt out into the Earth, as he made an Attempt againſt Heaven, hath, with all Choler and Wrath, vomited out of his Mouth whole Floods of Perſecutions, one rolling inceſſantly upon the back of another, to overwhelm the Church in final Ruin and Deſtruction. And to make the Ocean of her Miſeries, as it were, incomprehenſible, and beyond thought, how have many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, and greateſt Potentates of the Earth, added a Red Sea thereto, by ſhedding the Blood of the Saints, without end or meaſure? The Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians felt the ſmart firſt, and their Fellow-ſervants have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32727:8"/>been partakers of their Sufferings frequently unto theſe Days. And thoſe who would come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they might not be partakers of her Sins, nor receive of her Plagues, have had a reſtraint put upon them, that they ſhould not; ſo that when <hi>perſecuted in one City,</hi> or Kingdom, they could not enjoy the Priviledge, given them by Chriſt in his Goſpel, to <hi>flee into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if we hear <hi>Zion</hi> bemoaning her ſelf thus, over all the Evils and Calamnities brought upon her, for all the hurt and havock that the Church of God hath ſuffer'd, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World unto this Day, beſides what ſhe fears may yet happen, and by ſome diffidence ariſing thereby, ſhe ſhould queſtion whether her <hi>Baſis,</hi> or Foundation be ſo ſtrong, that it ſhall remain perpetually firm for the time to come, againſt the force and fury of her implacable and reſtleſs Foes.</p>
                  <p>For her Comfort, and to reſolve her Doubts herein, let her know, that all her Loſs is Gain. Thoſe that die for their good Faith, go from Warring and Fighting here, in the Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, unto the Mother Church of all, Triumphant in Heaven. Thoſe, that amidſt a World of Miſeries below, were Faithful unto Death, aſcend into Regions of Bliſs above, to receive Crowns of Eternal Life.</p>
                  <p>Neither is the number of her Members extenuated or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed on Earth, by their departure from us for the Teſtimony of Chriſt, according to that common ſaying, <hi>Sanguis Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae;</hi> the bare Letter whereof is, That the Blood of Martyrs is the Seed of the Church, which the ſence and meaning conſtrues thus, That the more the Church of God is perſecuted, the more at laſt ſhe multiplies: Like good Seed caſt into good Ground, it brings forth Thirty, Sixty, and an Hundred ſold.</p>
                  <p>And often, not only is the number augmented, but their Faith is the more vigorous and active too; for, <hi>Marcet ſine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſario virtus, ſed creſcit ſub pondere,</hi> their Faith doth fade and fail, and is not ſo lively and brisk, as when quickened by the Power and Trials of the Enemy, (as <hi>Rome</hi> when <hi>Carthage</hi> was deſtroyed, fell to Luxury). But under the preſſure and weight of Sufferings it gets ground, and becomes of a more diffuſive Nature; and therefore the Exerciſe and Trials of the Faith of the Beſt Men, are meant of God for good.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32727:9"/>
                  <p>And furthermore, the Church is to remember, that her Sins are the cauſe of all her Sorrows, without which ſhe would have neither Pain nor Grief; nor any Enemy could Moleſt or Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her. For it is ſtill with her as it was in the Days of the Judges of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And we read in the ſecond Chapter of their Book, that <hi>the People feared the Lord all the Days of</hi> Joſhua, <hi>and all the Days of the Elders, that out-lived</hi> Joſhua, and ſo long it was well with them; but afterwards it is ſaid, <hi>The Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>did evil in the ſight of the Lord, and ſerved</hi> Baalim: <hi>And they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fook the Lord God of their Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. The ill Conſequence whereof was this, <hi>The Anger of the Lord was hot againſt</hi> Iſrael, and <hi>he delivered them into the hands of Spoilers, that ſpoiled them, and he ſold them into the Hands of their Enemies round about: So that they could not any longer ſtand before their Enemies. Whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they went out, the Hand of the Lord was againſt them for Evil, as the Lord had ſaid, and as the Lord had ſworn unto them, and they were greatly diſtreſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now Sin was the cauſe of all this Trouble, and ſo it hath been, and will be the Origin and Fountain of all Miſery: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is the Duty of the Church and People of God, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto his Chaſtiſements, without complaint or murmuring, becauſe they deſerve them, and, it may be, want Correction to make them better. And then alſo we are to bear the Croſs pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, as did Chriſt, the Author of our Salvation; that ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our ſhare with him in Sufferings, we may be partakers of his Glory.</p>
                  <p>But yet could not all theſe Enemies, nor all the mighty num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them, ſince the World began, root out the true Church of God, from having a Being in the face of the Earth, neither ſhall they ſo prevail, ſo long as the Sun and Moon endure; but when they have done all they can, they ſhall themſelves bear the Puniſhment: <hi>They ſhall reel to and fro, and ſtagger like a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Man, and be at their Wits-end,</hi> when the Miſchief intended by them to others ſhall fall on their own Heads. And therefore, though they ſhould ſeek to deſtroy <hi>Jacob</hi> by <hi>Inchantments,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Divination;</hi> and alſo, to that end, ſhould uſe Pious Frauds, and Religious Stratagems againſt the Church, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fair and ſpecious pretences outwardly; build Altars, and offer Sacrifices, even whole Hecatombs, without number on them: Though they ſhould preſent Heaven with never ſo many Gifts,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32727:9"/>and Dedicate all the Gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> unto it, and pray Night and Day unto God, unto Angels, and Saints, and join thereto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many <hi>Ave Maries</hi> unto the Bleſſed Virgin, and Court her with never ſo many Titles of the greateſt Honour and Power in Heaven; creating her Queen Regent there, with full Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over her Son, to make him do whatſoever ſhe ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him: Yet not all this, nor much more, that they can do, ſhall any whit prevail. Nothing thereof ſhall ſerve their turn againſt that Holy Church they would deſtroy, but ſhe ſhall ſtand firm againſt all the Attempts of her Enemies, whatſoever they be; though their Folly (that is ſo great) be Converted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fury, and their Malice be thereby the deeper, yet in their fierceſt Rage ſhall they be weak, and like <hi>Water ſpilt on the ground;</hi> or as <hi>the Duſt before the Wind, ſo ſhall the Angel of the Lord ſcatter them.</hi> For, <hi>ſurely there is no Enchantment againſt</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>neither is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael; which intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth my</p>
                  <p>Second Propoſition, <hi>That the Church hath been, and ſhall be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to abide in ſafety, by the Protection and good Providence of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For it is He that keeps her as the Apple of his Eye. It is the Eternal God that is her Refuge. It is he that beateth down all her Enemies, and <hi>beareth her on Eagles Wings</hi> above them all, and brings her unto himſelf. And it is God, that <hi>maketh his Angels Spirits, and his Miniſters Flames of Fire,</hi> in their order to attend on every good Member of his Church, and ſurround them all with Horſes and Chariots of Fire, againſt the Fury of the Enemy. He wrought ſundry times, and in divers manners, ſtrange and wonderful Deliverances, for the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> time after time, when they repented of their Sins, and cried unto him, he raiſed up a Deliverer to them, who delivered them. So he raiſed up his <hi>Anointed Cyrus,</hi> to looſe the Bonds and Fetters of the Seventy Years Captivity; to let the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers return free to their own Land; inſomuch that he made a Proclamation, and put it alſo in Writing, concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifying of the Temple, or Houſe of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. Here was Joy after much Sorrow, a ſweet Refreſhment of Pleaſure, after the Wormwood and Gall of ſo long an Affliction in a ſtrange Land.</p>
                  <p>And ſo after the Days, wherein our Saviour himſelf cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Earth with a ſinful Generation of Men; and as he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32727:10"/>had ſuffered, ſo left he his Followers to a wide World of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, yet how did God deliver his Apoſtles? St. <hi>Peter</hi> out of Priſon by the Conduct and Miniſtry of an Angel; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> frequently out of Perils of divers kinds.</p>
                  <p>And though Ten great Perſecutions raged againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to devour them by ſo great a Flood, caſt out of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Mouth, to carry away, if poſſible, by its violence, the Woman that brought forth the Man-child; yet all could not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Curſed Deſign: And the Efforts of thoſe perſecuting Emperors of <hi>Rome, Nero, Domitian, Decius,</hi> and the reſt, were all in vain, as to the utter Extirpation of Chriſtianity; though they cauſed whole Clouds of <hi>Martyrs</hi> to Seal their Faith with their own Blood, and endeavoured to aboliſh the very Name of Chriſt, by inflicting moſt Cruel Deaths and Tortures upon his Saints on Earth. Nay <hi>Diocleſian</hi>'s Perſecution, the laſt of the Ten, though of a long continuance, and ſo hot and ſevere, that it is ſaid ſome Thouſands were ſlain almoſt every Day in the Year: And who being a Prince of ſuch infinite Ambition, that he commanded himſelf to be worſhipped as God, and therefore had ſo great an Antipathy to Chriſtianity, that his whole Reign might be called one perpetual Perſecution; yet it pleaſed God to preſerve his Church ſtill: Though the <hi>Woman</hi> was forced to fly into the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> yet there <hi>had ſhe a place pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of God,</hi> and there was ſhe ſed. She had a Being ſtill, though under a Cloud, and in Obſcurity.</p>
                  <p>But then, after ſo many black and diſmal Days, the Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhine clear, thoſe Clouds of <hi>Egyptian</hi> Darkneſs were by the good Providence of God diſpell'd, and Heaven, with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Aſpect, did ſmile on the Church, that had held out ſo long, and kept her Faith, under the Sword, and fiery Trials of ſo many perſecuting Tyrants. And Emperors themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Nurſing-fathers unto her. <hi>Conſtantius Chlorus</hi> was, as it is ſaid, (though not a known Chriſtian himſelf, yet) a Friend to thoſe that were ſuch. But next after him, his Son <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> the firſt Emperor, that countenanced the Goſpel, and embraced it publickly, was a moſt Loving Father to the Church, who Nurſed her tenderly, when he became a moſt Zealous Profeſſor of her Faith, and the Goſpel of Chriſt, by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Providence, as it is deſcribed in Hiſtory, after this manner; At the ſame time that he was ſaluted Emperor in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32727:10"/>
                     <hi>Britain, Maxentius</hi> was choſen at <hi>Rome</hi> by the Praetorian Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and <hi>Licinius</hi> named Succeſſor by <hi>Maximianus</hi> the aſſociate of his Father <hi>Chlorus</hi> (whereby he had two Competitors for the Empire). Being penſive and ſolicitous upon theſe Diſtractions, he caſt his Eyes up towards Heaven, where he ſaw a lightſome Pillar in the form of a Croſs, wherein he read theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, hereby Conquer thou: As much as if it had been ſaid to him, Turn Chriſhian, and thou ſhalt get the Victory, and be Emperor of <hi>Rome.</hi> And it is further ſaid, That the next Night our Saviour appearing to him in a Viſion, commanded him to bear that Figure in his Standard, and he ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all his Enemies; this he performed, and was accordingly Victorious: For what could hinder him then, when once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Soldier of Chriſt, he had him for his Chief Captain or General, and all the Hoſts of Heaven to ſide with him?</p>
                  <p>Now if any Perſon hath not Faith enough to believe this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of this great Chriſtian Emperor's Converſion, that it was thus ſtrangely brought to paſs. Yet, that by the great Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God he was Converted to the True Faith, that he was a Nurſing-father to the Church of Chriſt, and a great Lover and Favourer of Chriſtians, and ſo in this reſpect, an Enemy to thoſe that were Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, and the Chriſtian Religion, no intelligent Perſon will doubt.</p>
                  <p>Now, beſides the many and wonderful Deliverances of the Church, in former Ages, we may meditate upon what great things God hath wrought for her in theſe Nations, ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: To recount them all is needleſs, for who is he that hath not heard of them? But to ſpeak once for all; it is worth our notice and obſervation, that as in the Year of our Lord, <hi>One Thouſand Five Hundred and Eighty Eight,</hi> a mighty and vaſt Navy, with Conſidence and Oſtentation enough, by the Vain-glorious Name of an <hi>Invincible Armada,</hi> was ſet out for the Deſtruction of us and our Church, which, by the good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, was defeated and ſcattered, and with Infamy came to nought: So, when time, that under God worketh all things, had ſpun out an Hundred Years more, making the next <hi>Eighty Eight</hi> Memorable and Glorious, there came forth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fleet</hi> or <hi>Navy,</hi> for our Help and Deliverance from appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Dangers, for the Security of our Religion, the Church, and Nation, and by the Bleſſing of God had Power to prevail,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32727:11"/>for our Good and Safety, under the Conduct of that Wiſe and Valiant Prince, who is now our Moſt Gracious King, and Mighty Deliverer: So that if our Enemies had but <hi>Egyptians</hi> Eyes in their Heads, and their Underſtanding in their Hearts, they might ſee and know, that <hi>this is the Finger of God,</hi> and that <hi>it is hard for</hi> them <hi>to kick againſt the pricks,</hi> and <hi>fight againſt God.</hi> Although he did once ſuffer him, in whoſe Strength they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all their Confidence, to take his Paſtime, like the <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> in the Waters, and for ſome time to ſhew his Power on the Deep. Yet may God one Day, when he cometh out boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his own Strength, <hi>put</hi> his <hi>Hook in</hi> his <hi>Noſe, and</hi> his <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in</hi> his <hi>Lips,</hi> and ſo give him proud <hi>Sennacherib</hi>'s Fate and Doom, with Shame and Confuſion make him glad to return, as well as he can, <hi>the way that he came.</hi> This let us hope for, becauſe God will defend his Church and People, to ſave them for his own ſake, and for all his Faithful Servants ſake, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Wings of his Almighty protection, we ſhall find ſhelter, and abide in ſafety, and <hi>the Stars in their Courſes ſhall fight againſt</hi> our Enemies.</p>
                  <p>But yet, by way of Application, this is upon condition, that we keep our ſelves ſo free from the Defilements of Sin, that Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity may not be our Ruin. For, to illuſtrate this, when <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> would have Curſed the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but had not power to do it, he told <hi>Balak, God did force him contrariwiſe to bleſs them,</hi> as it is in the 20th Verſe of this Chapter of my Text, <hi>Behold I have received commandment to bleſs, and he hath bleſſed, and I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe it.</hi> And then enſues the true Cauſe of this Bleſſedneſs in the next Verſe, <hi>He hath not beheld Iniquity in</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither hath he ſeen Perverſeneſs in</hi> Iſrael. The People were Holy and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſo long God's Eſpecial Preſence was with them, as the following words do declare, <hi>The Lord his God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is among them.</hi> But yet, when a little after they were ſubjected to Sin, and committed Lewdneſs and Folly, and bowed down to other Gods, then God withdrew his gracious Preſence, and, inſtead thereof, ſent a Plague among them, which leſſened their number by <hi>Twenty and Four Thouſand,</hi> that were quickly ſwept away, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>Whereby we ſee, it is the Evil of Sin, that cauſeth the Evil of Puniſhment, one particular Act whereof is enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Divine Juſtice to ſtrike, and ſatisfied it muſt be, either by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32727:11"/>Contrition, and true Sorrow of Heart here, or Pain hereafter. And then how aggravating is it for Men to proceed ſtill in an Habit and Cuſtom of the higheſt Provocations, without any Remorſe or Conſideration at all of the Evil of their Doings? Notwithſtanding God's calls to Repentance and Amendment; at one time, by Judgments inflicted upon a People, or Nation; and at another time impendent, and hovering over their Heads, like a huge black Cloud, threatning a moſt violent Storm.</p>
                  <p>From which near and approaching Danger nevertheleſs, when God hath made a way for an eſcape, and a great Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, then for Men to be unthankful; after fears of Evil, to murmur at Mercy: To be pleaſed no way, neither in Danger, nor out of it, is a ſtrange, and almoſt, if not altogether, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable Crime; for the Sin of Ingratitude, in its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, muſt needs be very heinous and provoking in the Eyes of a moſt Wiſe, and a Good God; eſpecially when Mercies are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in their kind, and like to Miracles; then to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, even as <hi>Jonah,</hi> becauſe <hi>Nineveh</hi> was not deſtroyed: To be diſpleaſed at the great <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> under God, of our Deliverance; and in the Heart to deſire Spoilers to Invade the Land, is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and Spiteful. And in the Mind, to wiſh for, and bid welcome to the Forces of a known Foreign Tyrant, who know no other, than to Burn and Deſtroy, when and where they have Power, and thus in effect to hope for Slavery, is a Wickedneſs and Folly, ſcarce, or not at all, to be parallei'd in any Hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>But now let the People of this Land ſhew themſelves unto the World, to be a Wiſe and Underſtanding Nation, let us all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our ſelves to be Men of Reaſon and Prudence, by being ſenſible of our late wonderful Deliverance, and knowing our preſent Happineſs. Let us be juſt unto God, by due praiſes to him, for this great Bleſſing upon us. Let the <hi>Te Deum</hi> be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in our Mouths, and the <hi>Triſagion</hi> ſounding out of our Lips, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Hoſts; with continual <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs; praiſe ye the Lord, praiſe, O ye Servants of the Lord, praiſe ye the Name of the Lord. O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good, for his Mercy endureth for ever. Let the Redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, whom he hath Redeemed from the Hand of the Enemy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And next, let us render unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> our due Tribute of Thanks, and Faithful Obedience, for venturing his Life for us,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32727:12"/>and Fighting our Battels. Nay this to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> both let us give, for their Zeal and Courage, and great Conduct of Affairs; for their good Will and tender Affection towards us all. Let us be ſenſible of our Happy Condition, under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of their moſt Auſpicious Government; and let us Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate one another therein; becauſe they will, by the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, ſupport and defend us, and our Religion, our Laws and Liberties. And then let us manifeſt unto the World, that we do fully know, and underſtand, and are ſatisfied, that God hath undeſervedly and greatly Bleſſed us with a moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, Wiſe, and Gracious King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> For whom let us pray, That <hi>God will grant Them an Happy Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the King's Safe Return from the Wars with Victory and all Good Succeſs; and that He will Establiſh Them in the Thrones of Their Kingdoms, and Enable Them to lay a laſting Foundation to the Peace and Tranquility of Our Church, and Theſe Nations:</hi> That They may <hi>be Victorious over All Their Enemies, both by Sea and Land; and ſtrengthen the Hands of Their Allies, againſt the Great Troubler of our</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Common Diſturber of all</hi> Chriſtendom; <hi>that Their Reign may be Proſperous, and Their Days many; Their People Loyal and Dutiful Subjects unto Them: And that They may Both ſo ſerve God here, that when He ſhall be pleaſed to Call Them from theſe Earthly Crowns, unto Himſelf, He may Crown Them with Eternal Glory and Felicity in the higheſt Heavens.</hi> In which Prayer let the whole Nation join together; and to it now, <hi>let all</hi> this Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>ſay, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:12"/>
                  <p>The GLORY Departed.</p>
                  <p>SERMON II. ON THE DEATH Of Our Late Moſt Gracious Queen Mary II. Of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
                  <p>Preached in <hi>Mortlake</hi>-Church in <hi>Surrey,</hi> on the Third Day of <hi>March,</hi> 1694.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32727:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:14"/>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32727:14"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ISAM. iv. 22.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>—<hi>The Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael:—</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>IN a moſt ſad and lamentable manner <hi>is this Scripture</hi> of late <hi>fulfill'd in your Ears.</hi> And <hi>Oh! that my Head were Waters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. <hi>9.1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and mine Eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might weep Day and Night</hi> for the unſpeakable Loſs of that Glory, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the ſurpriſing Deceaſe of Our Moſt Gracious and Pious Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> of Ever Bleſſed Memory. The Solemnity of whoſe Funeral beging near, it may be proper now to ſpeak of her Majeſty; <hi>of whom we ſaid, Under</hi> Her <hi>Shadow,</hi> with the Joint-protection of His Moſt Excellent and Sacred Majeſty King <hi>William, we ſhall live among</hi> our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Enemies; And through the Mercy of God, who gave unto us thoſe two Unparallel'd Virtuous Princes, we ſhall, they Reigning over us, in defiance of the proudeſt Powers, enjoy our Religion, our Laws, and Liberties; have all Rights, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, and Privileges reſtored to our Nation, ſetled and confirmed unto us, and our Poſterity on a laſting Foundation. Yea, although we have loſt the Beſt of Princeſſes, we ſtill hope by God's Grace for thoſe Bleſſings, through our Surviving So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign's Auſpicious and Valiant Endeavours; through his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the great Counſels of our Auguſt Aſſembly, the thrice Honourable Senators of our Land.</p>
                  <p>But alas! the unexpected <hi>Breach,</hi> that is made, is Diſmal and Amazing; when God had given us a double portion of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Love and Kindneſs in two ſuch Religious and Hercick Princes, ſo Tender and Affectionate, ſo Careful and Solicitous for our Welfare and Happineſs in all reſpects; of the good of <hi>Christendom;</hi> yea, what in them lay of the whole World, for the Eſtabliſhment of Peace and Quietneſs therein, as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be obtain'd. That by them, next under God, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32727:15"/>of <hi>Janus</hi> might, as well as 'twas in <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus</hi>'s Reign, be ſhut up, and Wars ceaſe. That if not fully, yet in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at leaſt, that glorious Prophecy of <hi>Micah</hi> might be fulfill'd, <hi>They ſhall beat their Swords into Plow-ſhares,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mic. <hi>4.3, 4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and their Spears into Pruning-books: Nation ſhall not lift up a Sword againſt Nation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall they learn War any more. But they ſhall ſit every Man under his Vine, and under his Fig-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For it was the united and conſtant Study of both Our <hi>Dread Soveraigns,</hi> to do good in a moſt abundant manner to all: It was their delight; their Bowels yearned after it, that Men might enjoy Liberty and Property. They were unanimous and fixed in ſuch Principles, as chiefly conduced to the Glory of God, and the true Intereſt of Mankind, both in Sacred and Civil Concerns. Their Royal Thoughts were always employ'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with a ſweet and agreeable Harmony, knit together with the Golden Chain of Princely Love and Affection; wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting in ſound Judgment, and moving together into the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Reaſon, for the real Good of others, rather (we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) than their own Greatneſs; prompted by Noble and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Sentiments to the Deliverance hitherto effected, and not out of private Ambitious Deſigns, as Men may well think, upon mature Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>All this, and more of the like good and high Nature, which we either know not, or cannot think of, being put together, is it not melancholy and aſtoniſhing, that we have loſt Our Moſt Gracious and Religious Queen, the Great Patroneſs of our Church, and Mighty Defender of our Faith. And thereby <hi>the Glory is departed from</hi> us; <hi>the Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Which words of the Text, before we proceed any further on our mournful Subject, claim ſome Conſideration from us, as to the Original Reaſon and Occaſion, for which they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Which we find to be the ſad and woful News that on a ſudden was heard in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> cauſing great Weeping and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For we find in this Chapter, there had been two ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Battels fought between the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> in both which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were worſted. In the former they loſt <hi>about Four Thouſand Men.</hi> Upon this ill ſucceſs, they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by the Advice of their Elders, to <hi>fetch the Ark of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord out of</hi> Shiloh <hi>unto them,</hi> hoping for Preſervation and Victory thereby, in theſe words, <hi>That when it cometh among
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32727:15"/>us, it may ſave us out of the hand of our Enemies,</hi> Ver. 3. And fetched accordingly it was: Upon the Arrival whereof in their Camp, it was ſaluted <hi>with a great</hi> and general <hi>ſhout</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that the Earth rang again,</hi> to the great Terror and Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at firſt of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> pronouncing thereupon <hi>Woes</hi> to themſelves, for that they thought the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was come into the Camp of his People; and no doubt it might have been ſo with good effect, had not their Sins lain in the way. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> thinking their Caſe deſperate, upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Preſence of that God againſt them, who had before-time ſo fatally overthrown the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> took ſuch Reſolutions as <hi>Warriors</hi> have ſometimes done, when driven thereto by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of any Relief; for they animated one another to frame themſelves to their Condition, and Fight as deſperate as their Caſe ſeem'd to be, that they might not fall into the Power of, and be in Bondage to their Enemies; thus encouraging and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting themſelves, <hi>Be ſtrong, and quit your ſelves like Men, O ye</hi> Philiſtines, <hi>that ye be not Servants to the</hi> Hebrews, <hi>as they have been to you, quit your ſelves like Men, and Fight,</hi> Ver. 9. The <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> on the other ſide, hoping for that which the others fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God was amongſt them, and would puſh down their Enemies; but give them a Victorious and Joyful Day, join'd in Battel with thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> from whom they received a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and more bloody Overthrow than the firſt, of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry eſpecially; <hi>for</hi> now <hi>there fell of</hi> Iſrael <hi>Thirty Thouſand Footmen:</hi> And this not all neither, as the ſad ſequel of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry makes out, for the <hi>Ark</hi> of God, their great Hope and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was gone too, 'twas taken Captive; and <hi>the two Sons of</hi> Eli, Hophni <hi>and</hi> Phinehas, were <hi>ſlain.</hi> The bitter News where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of coming to old <hi>Eli</hi>'s Ears, was preſent Death alſo to him, fainting and falling <hi>backward</hi> at ſuch mention being made of the <hi>Ark of God,</hi> by which fall he died.</p>
                  <p>The unwelcome Relation of all which fearful Tragedy, and doleful Tidings, cauſed <hi>his Daughter-in-law,</hi> Phinehas <hi>Wife,</hi> great with Child, to Travail, and have <hi>her Pains</hi> come <hi>upon her,</hi> and even to breathe out her Soul alſo, without minding or regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Comforts, no, not that of a Son being Born by her, any farther than before ſhe expired, to give him a Name of a proper ſignification to the Calamity of the then preſent time, which was <hi>Ichabod,</hi> expreſſing thereby the Loſs of Glory, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32727:16"/>chiefly for the Ark's ſake, <hi>ſaying, The Glory is departed from</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, (becauſe <hi>the Ark of God was taken, and becauſe of her Father-in-law, and her Husband). And ſhe ſaid, The Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for the Ark of God is taken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this <hi>Ark</hi> was glorious, as it was God's own Ordinance, made by his expreſs Order, who appointed both the Matter and Form of it,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> how it ſhould be made, and with what; its <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions</hi> alſo, and <hi>Appendages;</hi> and that it ſhould be overlaid <hi>within and without with pure Gold,</hi> and be adorn'd with <hi>a Crown of Gold upon it round about.</hi> It was not lawful for any to bear or carry it but the <hi>Levites:</hi> Wherefore God ſhewed his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure at King <hi>David</hi>'s putting it upon a Cart, to bring it from <hi>Abinadab</hi>'s Houſe, when he ſmote <hi>Uzzah</hi> for touching it, being Sacred and Glorious, when ſo unadviſedly degraded; which Royal <hi>David</hi>'s own words confirm, 1 Chron. 15.13. <hi>The Lord our God made a Breach upon us, for that we ſought him not after the due order:</hi> Foraſmuch as it was the Office of the <hi>Levites,</hi> or <hi>Prieſts,</hi> (they being of the ſame <hi>Tribe</hi>) to bear it, as Perſons ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and conſecrated to that Service. Glorious the <hi>Ark</hi> was far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet by the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Propitiatory</hi> or <hi>Mercy-ſeat</hi> of pure Gold, placed above upon it, with the two Golden <hi>Cherubims</hi> on the two ends thereof, and that the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> or Two Tables of the <hi>Law</hi> were put into it, of the <hi>Law</hi> or Ten Commandments, which God ſpake with ſo great Terror on <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> and therefore 'tis ſtiled in Holy Writ, <hi>The</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Numb. <hi>10.33.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ark of the Covenant, and the</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Numb. <hi>4.5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ark of the Teſtimony,</hi> with many other Glorious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Appellations, as, <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 35.</note> 
                     <hi>holy Ark, the</hi>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ark of the Lord, the</hi>
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.18.</note> 
                     <hi>Ark of God, the</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Ark of his Strength.</hi> It was kept in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> or <hi>Holy of Holieſt,</hi> in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; and afterwards brought into the Oracle of the Houſe, to the moſt Holy Place of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple. The Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſeems poſitive that it had in it the Pot; <hi>The Golden Pot</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of Manna, and</hi> Aaron<hi>'s Rod that budded,</hi> as well as the <hi>Twe Tables of the Covenant.</hi> And therefore becauſe 'tis ſaid, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.9. to which is conſonant, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.10. that <hi>there was nothing in the Ark, ſave the Two Tables of Stone, which</hi> Moſes <hi>put there at</hi> Horeb, <hi>when the Lord made a Covenant with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>when they came out of the Land of</hi> Egypt; becauſe of this ſaying, ſome think the Apoſtle's meaning is rather, that <hi>the Golden Pot of Manna,</hi> and <hi>Aaons Famons Rod</hi> that <hi>brought forth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32727:16"/>buds, and bloomed Bloſſoms, and yielded Almonds,</hi> were only put into the Tabernacle, meaning that part of the Tabernacle, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſecond Vail, called, <hi>The Holieſt of all,</hi> according to that of <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.34. <hi>As the Lord commanded</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo</hi> Aaron <hi>laid it</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Pot of <hi>Manna</hi>) <hi>up before the Teſtimony;</hi> to the end it was that it might be kept for their Generations. And <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.10. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>bring</hi> Aaron<hi>'s Rod again before the Teſtimony to be kept for a Token againſt the Rebels.</hi> So that both were to be preſerved before the Teſtimony, or the Two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Law; but whether in the <hi>Ark</hi> with them, or out of it before the <hi>Ark,</hi> and ſo before the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> which was inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein, is the queſtion. If we think both were put into the Ark before the Teſtimony, we muſt judge they were taken out by ſome means before <hi>Solomon</hi> ſent for the Ark: Or elſe that theſe words, <hi>There was nothing in the Ark ſave the Two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Stone which</hi> Moſes <hi>put there at</hi> Horeb, are to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that only thoſe Two Tables were placed then alone in the Ark, when the Prieſts brought it <hi>into his place into the Oracle of the Houſe,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Temple) <hi>to the moſt holy place under the Wings of the Cherubims,</hi> 1 King. 8.6. Or elſe, becauſe it ſeems plain by the Apoſtle's words well obſerved in the Original, that both the Pot of <hi>Manna,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s <hi>Rod</hi> were in the Ark, as well as the Two Tables of the Covenant: It may be ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for reconciling the whole, to ſuppoſe according to <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact,</hi> that though in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s time there was nothing in the Ark, but the Two Tables; yet, in ſome time afterwards, the Pot of <hi>Manna</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod were put therein alſo.</p>
                  <p>But to proced, the Ark was Glory chiefly, becauſe of the Glorious Preſence and Majeſty of God on the Mercy-ſeat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Cherubims, that his Name was called on it, that at it they enquired or asked Counſel. For there was the Divine Oracle, from thence God himſelf did vouchſafe to ſpeak, as he told <hi>Moſes, There I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee, from above the Mercy-ſeat, from between the two Cherubims, which are upon the Ark of the Teſtimony, of all things which I will give thee in Commandment unto the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Exod</hi> 25.22. And it was a ſign of God's Eſpecial Preſence among his People; a ſignal inſtance whereof was that in <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s time, at the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> paſage through the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> when the Ark paſſing before the People into that River, as ſoon as <hi>the Feet of the Prieſts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32727:17"/>that bare it</hi> were dipped in the brim of the Water, at the time of its overflowing in Harveſt, <hi>the Waters which came down from above, ſtood and roſe up upon an heap, and thoſe that came down failed, and were cut off;</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> that ſupported the Ark ſtanding <hi>firm on dry ground in the midſt of</hi> the River, <hi>until all the People were paſſed clean over</hi> on dry ground alſo, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 3. And <hi>Moſes</hi> before at the Ark's ſetting forward, as certain of God's Preſence, uſed this form of Speech: <hi>Riſe up, Lord, and let thine Enemies be ſcattered, and let them that hate thee, flee before thee. And when it reſted, he ſaid, Return, O Lord, unto the many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.35, 36.</p>
                  <p>And ſo Glorious was the <hi>Ark,</hi> and ſo Wonderfully was God's Preſence with it, though in Captivity by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and brought into the Houſe or Temple of their god <hi>Dagon,</hi> that their <hi>Dagon</hi> could not ſtand before it; his place could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and hold him faſt from proſtration, for down he <hi>fell upon his Face to the Earth,</hi> as it were, ſaluting it with the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as one would think, if <hi>Dagon</hi> had been endued with any the leaſt Life or Senſe. And when he was re-eſtabliſhed in his place, and faſtened perhaps with much Art, down again he fell <hi>upon his Face to the ground before the Ark,</hi> with a worſe Fate than before, for now total Deſtruction came upon the Inſenſible god; he was daſhed to pieces, <hi>his Head and Hands cut off upon the Threſhold, and no more than his Stump left to him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next after this defeat of their Idol, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> themſelves very ſorely ſmarted, and felt the Mighty Power and Preſence of God with the Ark, for <hi>the Hand of the Lord was heavy upon them of</hi> Aſhdod, deſtroying them, and ſmiting <hi>them with Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods,</hi> their very <hi>Coaſts</hi> not exempted from the ſad Calamity. And when upon Conſultation with their <hi>Lords</hi> how they ſhould remove the Evil from them, they carried it about to <hi>Gath,</hi> then Wo to all of that <hi>City, ſmall and great,</hi> an heavy Deſtruction up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <hi>by the Hand of the Lord:</hi> And when ſent to Ekron, <hi>the</hi> Ekronites <hi>cried out,</hi> as ſenſible of the Fate of others, and what was falling upon them, <hi>Saying, They have brought about the Ark of the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to us, to ſlay us and our People,</hi> as it came to paſs, <hi>for there was a deadly Destruction throughout all the City, the Hand of God was very heavy there</hi> alſo, making <hi>the Cry of the City go up to Heaven,</hi> 1 Sam. 5. So that better it had been for the <hi>Philiſtimes</hi> never to have touched the Holy Ark of the Covenant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32727:17"/>of the Lord, for it was the worſt Captive to them that ever they took, it made ſuch work and woful ſlaughter amongſt them; and forced they were to ſend it away, and ask Counſel of their Prieſts and Diviners with what they ſhould ſend it to its place; whoſe Advice was, <hi>not to ſend it empty, but in any wiſe to return the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>a Treſpaſs-Offering.</hi> And that they ſhould more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over <hi>give Glory unto the God of</hi> Iſrael, giving them ſome Hopes thereby of a Releaſe from the preſent Puniſhment, thus, <hi>Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he will lighten his Hand from off you, and from off your gods, and from off your Land,</hi> 1 Sam. 6.</p>
                  <p>So that from hence we may conclude alſo, that <hi>Eli</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-in-law might with ſtrength of Reaſon on her ſide ſay, <hi>The Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>becauſe the Ark of God was taken;</hi> which when preſent with them was Salvation to them, if Sin did not bar out the Bleſſing; and 'twas Death and great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to their grand Enemies, when amongſt them, tho' in Captivity, plaguing and ſlaying them in a very large meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, ſo glorious was the <hi>Ark,</hi> and holy, that altho' the <hi>Bethſhemites</hi> rejoiced at the ſight thereof, upon its arrival out of the <hi>Philiſtine</hi>'s Country into their own, and <hi>offered Burnt-Offerings, and ſacrificed Sacrifices unto the Lord the ſame Day;</hi> yet becauſe they preſumed to pry and look into it, <hi>he ſmote of the People Fifty Thouſand Threeſcore and Ten Men:</hi> to their great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, with Aſtoniſhment, ſaying, <hi>Who is able to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this holy Lord God?</hi> 1 Sam. 6. But on the other hand, we find it procured a Bleſſing to <hi>Obed-Edom,</hi> and all he had, when Three Months in his Houſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. from whence <hi>David</hi> brought it <hi>into the City of</hi> David <hi>with gladneſs,</hi> and great ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, his own Royal Perſon Dancing <hi>before the Lord with all his might, with Sacrifices and Offerings; ſhouting, and the ſound of the Trampet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Very glorious alſo was the <hi>Ark</hi> in a farther proſpect than yet we have mention'd; or either, perhaps, Old <hi>Eli,</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi>'s Wife, or any of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did perceive, or think of, when 'twas captivated, that is, in its mighty Symbols and Prefigurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, its Noble Type and Repreſentation of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> in the Evangelical <hi>Oeconomy;</hi> its glorious Figures thereof, as to it ſelf, and all that belong'd to it, or was preſerv'd and contain'd in it, of which we have not time now to ſpeak. So that Glory it was to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their then preſent honourable Thoughts and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32727:18"/>Conceptions of it, according to what they did know, and far greater Glory in what they did not underſtand or conceive.</p>
                  <p>Sad then! that the <hi>Heathen</hi> their Enemies ſhould both over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them in Battel, and take it Captive; their great Hope be ſuddenly gone with Terrour and Amazement! It was enough for a deep and general Mourning in all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> enough to make all Diſconſolate, and ſome to bid Adieu to all Comforts here, to take leave of the World; and, like Old <hi>Eli,</hi> and his Daughter-in-law, yield up the Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And now,</hi> to return from one ſad Scene to another, from <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>'s Loſs to our own. Their Sins had provoked God to afflict them with a terrible ſtroke. And ſo have ours cauſed him in his Diſpleaſure to take from us that great undeſerved Bleſſing, which in his Mercy he gave unto us, in the Royal Perſon of his Anointed, that Wiſe and Incomparable Princeſs, for whom <hi>the Mourners</hi> do now <hi>go about the Streets;</hi> our Late Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lady the <hi>Queen,</hi> whoſe Princely and Sublime Virtues were ſo numerous, and of ſuch a large ſize and ſubſtance, by the growth and perfection ſhe gave them, through her Moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Sacred Majeſty's daily Increaſe in all Goodneſs; that we may eaſier form a <hi>Galaxy,</hi> or Bright Circle of them in our Nobleſt and Loftieſt Conceptions; or fix them in the Orbs of our Minds, as whole Conſtellations of Stars of the firſt Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, than ſpeak clearly and fully of all thoſe ſhining Graces, which in her Living were viſible to the Eye of the World, but now are hid from our Eyes. But let the Memory of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and thoſe her Rich Ornaments be kept Sacred to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that the Generations to come may bleſs the Age ſhe lived in, and withal reprove the wilful Blindneſs, and blackeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of thoſe, who did not obſerve her Virtues, nor Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Eſteem her Royal Perſon with that Duty and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as became Men, who by her Enjoy'd the Bleſſings of Heaven above, and of the Earth beneath, Spiritual good things, and Temporal. She, who was the Glory of her Age and Sex, of our Church, and theſe Nations, to her own Greatneſs, and all her Royalties, giving Luſtre to the <hi>Throne,</hi> by her moſt Eminent Virtues, in great Wiſdom and Prudence Crown'd all her ſelf. So that I may make Application upon her great Fame,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.</note> as the <hi>Queen of Sheba</hi> did to <hi>Solomon: Happy</hi> were her <hi>Men, happy</hi> were thoſe her <hi>Servants, which</hi> did <hi>ſtand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32727:18"/>before</hi> her Majeſty, hearing her Wiſdom, her good and gracious Words, and obſerving her Piety and Religious Ways; a lively Pattern and Example to all about her, and who of both Sexes, and all Qualities, in Sorrow and Bitterneſs of Heart, have cauſed a Voice to be heard, like that of Rachel <hi>in</hi> Rama, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and Weeping, and great Mourning, Weeping</hi> for her Moſt Excellent Majeſty, <hi>and would not be comforted, becauſe ſhe is not;</hi> ſhe is not in the Land of the Living: And becauſe <hi>the Glory is</hi> thereby <hi>departed from</hi> them. And from us all of her Majeſty's Realms and Dominions, and many more parts of the World is, <hi>The Glory departed.</hi> So that we in great multitudes, Domeſtick and Foreign, may join with the Royal Palace, and take up a wailing for us all, that our <hi>Eyes</hi> may <hi>run down with Tears, and</hi> our <hi>Eye-lids guſh out with Waters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But while we mourn, let us not forget to make Honourable mention of her Majeſty yet further; and tho' we cannot paint out to the Life thoſe many Graces, which did conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her, or rather were implanted in her; yet let us Celebrate her Obſequies, and Revere her Aſhes, thoſe Sacred Remains, by ſo juſt a Commemoration of her Excellent Endowments, as the Confuſion of Grief and Wo in our Minds will permit.</p>
                  <p>Now, Virtue in general ſeem'd innate or connatural to her Majeſty, by that firmneſs of Root it had gain'd in her Royal Breaſt; and therefore thoſe many Species thereof, which Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, for ſome Thouſands of Years, have Diſputed and Reaſoned about, and Divines have much preached, and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of, were Eminently conſpicuous and demonſtrative in her. When ſhe was but a Child, they appear'd like <hi>Aurora</hi> before the Sun, as an happy <hi>Omen</hi> of what her Riper Years would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. She was then a bright <hi>Morning-ſtar,</hi> and like <hi>good King Joſiah</hi> began, when ſhe was young, <hi>to ſeek after God,</hi> Dedicated her ſelf unto him, and never deſiſted to the Day of her Death. Not forſaking God when ſhe felt the Thorns of her Crowns, and the multitude of Buſineſs throng'd her, or the Baits and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of Recreations might tempt her aſide. And as ſhe was <hi>ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord;</hi> ſo ſhe required her People and Servants to wait upon God, with a Vigilant Care her Self over all, who ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair unto the Chappel-Royal to attend on him in his Worſhip; imitating Faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>18.19.</hi>
                     </note> in commanding her <hi>Houſhold after</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32727:19"/>her <hi>to keep the way of the Lord;</hi> retrieving thereby the long loſt Honour of the Court, by Converting the Reigning Sins there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, through her Great Example and Pious Authority into Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Services. Sitting therein a Queen to do the Will of the Lord, and not of Men. And in all reſpects her Virtues ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Foundation of thoſe Vices, which had Triumph'd too much, threat'ned their total, and in part, at leaſt, wrought their Deſtruction. This made her truly Great, added much to her High and Illuſtrious Birth, and to her Perſon on the Throne.</p>
                  <p>And in all reſpects her Qualifications enforced and drew a lively pattern from her, for all to profit by, according to their ſeveral States and Conditions.</p>
                  <p>As a Queen and a Ruler, let Kings, and all Princes follow her with the higheſt Emulation, if with her they will take God's Directions, amongſt King <hi>David</hi>'s laſt words, into their Books of Politicks, how to Govern; which Divine Leſſon was her Majeſty's grand and principal Point, in the whole Compaſs of her Government, how to ſteer by, and which way to move: The Needle pointing always in her Thoughts to theſe, and the like holy Inſtructions, <hi>He that ruleth over Men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God, and he ſhall be as the light of the Morning, when the Sun riſeth, even a Morning without Clouds, as the tender Graſs ſpringing out of the Earth by clear ſhining after Rain,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Which Sacred Aphoriſm herein ſeems to have been the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rule and Line ſhe meaſured her Royal Thoughts, Words, and Actions by, all her Reign; the holy Balance in which ſhe firſt weighted every proceeding, through the whole Series of her great Affairs. And ſo ſhe anſwered likewiſe this Divine Simile, <hi>as in Water Face anſwereth to Face,</hi> truly and exactly. Let it be ſaid then of our moſt Devout and Religious Queen, that, like holy <hi>David,</hi> ſhe <hi>was after God's own Heart.</hi> With <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and other Pions Kings, She <hi>did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> And like good King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> ſhe <hi>declined neither to the right Hand, nor to the left.</hi> Mercy and Juſtice reſided in the Throne with her; the former render'd her very Compaſſionate; but yet her Prudence and Magnanimity were ſuch, as ſhewed her how ſhe ſhould <hi>not bear the Sword in vain,</hi> ſhe being the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and <hi>Miniſter of God.</hi> And as ſhe was in high Authority, ſo was ſhe above all idle and vulgar Cenſures, or what was lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and mean.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32727:19"/>
                  <p>Conſider her Majeſty as a Wife. Our Great Monarch, whom ſhe hath left behind, and whom God in his Mercy long preſerve to us, will witneſs; yea, his great Grief of Heart doth Atteſt, how ſhe anſwer'd God's intent in the Creation of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that ſhe ſhould be<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
                     <hi>an help meet</hi> for Man. And according to the Apoſtolical Canons, with a meek and quiet Spirit ſhe gave <hi>reverence</hi> and yielded <hi>Subjection to her</hi> Royal <hi>Husband,</hi> who with mutual Returns of Endearment, according to like Holy Rules loved and honoured her <hi>as the weaker Veſſel;</hi> and his <hi>Glory</hi> alſo, For, the Man <hi>is the Image and Glory of God: but the Woman is the Glory of the Man,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.7.</p>
                  <p>She well deſerved the praiſe of the Virtuous Woman in the laſt Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>11, 12.</hi>
                     </note> For <hi>the Heart of her Husband</hi> did <hi>ſafely truſt in her,</hi> and <hi>ſhe</hi> did <hi>do him good, and not evil, all the Days of her Life. Her Candle</hi> did <hi>not</hi> go <hi>out by Night;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> for ſhe was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways mindful of her Duty and great Affairs. <hi>She looked well to her Houſhould, and</hi> did <hi>not</hi> eat <hi>the Bread of Idleneſs;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> for by her own Labours ſhe gave a New-birth to Work and Induſtry. <hi>Her Children,</hi> her good and dutiful Subjects I mean (for ſhe was a moſt Dear, Tender, and Compaſſionate Mother to us all) did <hi>ariſe up and call her bleſſed; her Husband alſo, and he</hi> praiſed <hi>her:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> Both whoſe mutual Affections and Returns of Love and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs united their Two Royal Perſons into One.</p>
                  <p>Think upon her Majeſty only as a Woman; but of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Excellency of Spirit, and largeneſs of Heart; of ſuch a Capacious Soul, and Radiancy of Mind, which is very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom found; and all tending more to Ambition of Goodneſs, than Deſire of Greatneſs: for <hi>Majeſty</hi> it ſelf could not tempt her to Pride in any thing. All which looked as happy preſages of bringing much Benefit to Mankind. But according to our purpoſe to deſcend from the Throne, let us view her, as if in a far lower Station amongſt her Sex, and ſay no more, but ſhe was a Woman: We ſhall find her Exemplary Virtues juſtly Claim an high precedency amongſt the whole Feminine Race. For, ſhew us ſuch another; when we call to witneſs her Majeſty's profound Piety and Devotion, her admired Meekneſs and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, her Sweet Temper, her Courteous Behaviour and Affability, yet preſerving Majeſty as a Queen, and her <hi>Moderation,</hi> which was <hi>known unto all Men;</hi> with that Serenity and Evenneſs of Mind alſo, that not Paſſion, but Reaſon moved and ſway'd her;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32727:20"/>that not eaſily lifted up, nor ſoon caſt down; Heroick and Free, yet Serious and Grave; Chearful, but without Levity. <hi>She</hi> opened <hi>her Mouth with Wiſdom, and in her Tongue</hi> was <hi>the Law of Kindneſs:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 31.26.</note> ſo Obliging and Diſcreet, that ſhe gain'd much upon the Affections even of her Enemies, and at leaſt often ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced the Tongues of unreaſonable Men, if ſhe could not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and alter their Judgments.</p>
                  <p>But to Crown all her Majeſty's Excellencies; ſhe was a holy and good Chriſtian, Zealous always in that <hi>one thing needful.</hi> Her unſpotted and unblameable Life and Converſation ſhined before Men, whilſt ſhe adorn'd the Goſpel of Chriſt with her Divine Graces; amongſt which we muſt again inroll her Piety, her unaffected Piety and Devotion, and all the aforemention'd Virtues, that belong to the Chriſtian Chain, with an unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Conſtancy in all her Duties. At the Head of all placing her ſervent Charity, that notable Badge of Chriſtianity; by which ſhe forgave many Affronts, and return'd none: but with an high ſort of Divine Clemency, <hi>did do good for evil,</hi> that her Light might ſhine; not for vain Oſtentation, far from it was ſhe, but for God's Glory, and an imitable Example to all others, and that by an entire Reſignation of her Will to Chriſt's Law, which himſelf exemplified, in pardoning and praying for his bittereſt Enemies,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>5.48.</hi>
                     </note> ſhe might <hi>be perfect, as</hi> her <hi>Father, which is in Heaven is perfect.</hi> Add we here her Boundleſs Charity in giving and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing to thoſe in Want: Alas! how many indigent and decay'd Perſons, whom her Royal Bounty and Pity Relieved, may bemoan themſelves? For her Charity was ſo unlimited, that few, if any but her ſelf, knew its utmoſt extent, or could give it a place wide enough in the vaſt Sphere of Imagination, that the compaſs of any Perſons Thought could comprehend it So Largely and Secretly, but Prudently withal, did ſhe ſtretch out her Hands to the Poor; yea, ſhe reached forth her Hands to the Needy. In general, ſhewing the Celeſtial Extraction of her Bleſſed Soul; when her Love and Charity was Univerſal, like that of her <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> which our Bleſſed Saviour hath ſet forth for our Imitation,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>5.45.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Who maketh his Sun to riſe on the evil, and on the good; and ſendeth Rain on the juſt, and on the unjuſt.</hi> After ſuch Charity, 'tis impoſſible for us to doubt of her Faith and Hope; but we may reſt aſſured, that both were very great.</p>
                  <p>And in ſhort, that ſhe might finiſh her Courſe with Joy, ſhe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32727:20"/>left not the great Work of Repentance to the laſt Call; but with the Wiſe Virgins, had her Lamp ready trimmed with Oyl in it, when the Bridegroom came, requiring her to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. So did ſhe watch, that when her Lord came, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediate Attendance, ſhe was not found Sleeping, nor Trifling or waſting away her precious time, but in the Exerciſe of all thoſe Chriſtian Graces, which, with her humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Reſignation to God's Will, through Chriſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her from the Corruptible Crowns here below, to an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Glorious Diadem above: when being <hi>Faithful to</hi> her <hi>Death, God gave</hi> her <hi>a Crown of Life.</hi> O to her moſt Happy and Glorious Second Coronation, in the higheſt Heavens, while we Mortals here below lament our Loſs, which is her Gain!</p>
                  <p>Thus have I Coaſted upon the Sea-ſhore of thoſe Graces and Virtues, which did ſhine on Earth in God's Anointed, and the Nurſing-Mother of our Church. And to launch out farther into the unfathomable Ocean of them, would require more time, with a ſtronger and larger Veſſel than my poor Talent can equip, and ſend out into ſo vaſt a Deep. An Ocean of them I mention, becauſe her <hi>Brook became a River, and</hi> her <hi>River became a Sea,</hi> a main Sea,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 24.31.</note> encompaſſing that whole Globe of Goodneſs, which was inherent in Her Majeſty, while ſhe acted in that great Sphere of Glory and Honour here, to ſave our Church, and theſe Nations, and the ſinking Parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> out of the Hands of their Potent and Common Enemy; which was purely Her Majeſty's Deſign, and is the Intent of the Mighty <hi>NASSAU,</hi> our Moſt Gracious King. And ſo to prevent a Ruſhing Deſtruction at Hand, and be the Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of many Nations and People from Ruin, by the Power put into their Hands through God's Merciful Providence, when the Nobles and Patriots of this Nation made their Requeſts to Their Majeſties; and the Peoples Cries, and humble Prayers and Solicitations by their Repreſentatives, wrought upon them to fill the Empty Throne therefore: This did not, I hope, infrinnge, or treſpaſs againſt the Fifth Commandment; when <hi>the People of the Land took</hi> them, <hi>and made</hi> them KING and QUEEN; their Crowns were even forced upon their Heads for the Salvation of our Church, and an Univerſal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the approaching Thraldom of a Foreign, but yet too Near, and too Potent an Enemy.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32727:21"/>
                  <p>I Challenge the World then to find out any Blemiſh or Spot in that Bright and moſt Clear Luminary, which now, the Curtain being drawn by the interpoſition of the great Vail and Canopy of the Heavens between her and us, ſuffers an Eclipſe in reſpect of our ſelves, but not of her, who enjoys <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> And yet Her Juſt Title here was Glorious too, <hi>MARY</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God QUEEN of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſhe added thereto the Choiceſt Ornaments, and moſt precious Rubies in her Crowns, the Tranſcendent Virtues of her moſt Comely and Graceful Perſon, with great Majeſty outwardly, and all Mercy within. So that as our Loſs is more than we can expreſs, ſo are her due Praiſes beyond all the Flowers of Rhetorick, and Art of Elocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>To Enumerate whoſe Virtues,</hi> as the Honourable Houſe of Commons ſaid, <hi>were to aggravate our Sorrow.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Addreſs to the King, <hi>Dec. 31.1694.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore a mighty Glory is departed from us, from the Chriſtian World; from all true Proteſtants chiefly, whoſe great Hope, and Joy, and Comfort ſhe was. And <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, tho' different in Religion from us, is not free from that Cloud of Darkneſs (whether ſenſible of it or no) that covers us by the Deceaſe of Her Moſt Excellent Majeſty. That ſuch an Unparallel'd Good Princeſs had ſo Juſt a Title to that Crown from Her Royal Anceſtors. For not to inſiſt upon all that we might, we will only mention, that our Valiant King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, but for the unjuſt Salique Law, was Heir to <hi>France</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of <hi>Philip the Fair;</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip</hi> Duke <hi>De Valois</hi> the other. See Sir <hi>R. Baker</hi>'s Chron. Life of <hi>Edw. 3.</hi>
                     </note> being then, according to ſome Hiſtories, the nearer in Blood of the Two Competitors, but drawing his Pedigree by a Female. Our Victorious King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth was Proclaim'd in <hi>France,</hi> as well as in <hi>England,</hi> to be the only Regent of that Realm, and Heir Apparent to that Crown. Whoſe Son, the Devout King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, was not only Proclaim'd, but with all uſual Ceremonies Crown'd in <hi>Paris</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now conſider we; what profound Veneration and Love had this our Great Princeſs gain'd in the Minds and Affections of thoſe beyond the Sea? What Univerſal Affliction is in thoſe Countries ſhe lived in? What huge Expreſſions of Sorrow for her Death do they give? <hi>Bleſſed be</hi> they <hi>of the Lord</hi> for the great Honour and Kindneſs they bare to her, when ſhe was in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32727:21"/>a ſtrange Country! But O the unexcuſeable Ingratitude of thoſe who did not the like to Her Majeſty in the Land of her Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity! When in other Parts of the World, ſhe ſo drew the Eyes and Hearts of all People after her, that ſhe was Beloved to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and was their great Deſire. But now ſhe is taken from us, as well as from them: <hi>Of whom the World was not worthy,</hi> ſhe being too Good and Virtuous for this Wicked and Adulterous Generation: And ſo like another <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> ſhe is fled to Heaven for a Reſting-place. And what Vows would we make? What Prayers would we offer up to Enjoy her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? What Returns of Praiſes and Thankſgivings would we preſent to God, in imitation of <hi>David</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they brought home the Ark? But alas! ſhe is gone, and ſhall not return to us: Which ſad Affliction is enough to damp and weigh down the greateſt Spirits, and to ſtrike us all Dumb, that we open not our Mouths, only by the way of Mourning and Humiliation, becauſe it is God's doing; who in the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of her Days, as well as of our Hopes, ſent forth his Decree to call her hence. To reverſe which (if it had been the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Will of the Lord) what Prayers, what Sighs and Tears were poured forth, and Means uſed, that the Diſtemper might not prevail over her, nor the King of Terrors Conquer by, to us, ſuch a bitter Deſtiny, cutting ſo early the Thread of ſo Precious a Life, ſo univerſally deſired long to remain? But Oh! the Hand of the Lord hath been very heavy upon us for our Sins, and to the utmoſt period of her Race here ſhe hath ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and unexpectedly run. So that with <hi>Job</hi> we may now ſay, Our <hi>Harp is turned to Mourning,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 30.31.</note> 
                     <hi>and</hi> our <hi>Organ into the Voice of them that weep,</hi> and with him ſit down in the Aſhes. And we may mourn with the <hi>mourning of</hi> Hadadrimmon <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Megiddon, as all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did for <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.11. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25.</note> And as <hi>the Prophet</hi> Jeremiah <hi>lamented for him,</hi> ſo have we cauſe to do the like for our Deceaſed Gracious QUEEN. Our Singing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Singing-women may, as theirs did a long time for that good King, ſpeak of her in their Lamentations. We have too ſad Cauſe to Tranſcribe a Copy from them, to make it an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and from their Original to write us a Book of Lamentations, and therein, <hi>The Joy of our Heart is ceaſed, our Dance is turned into Mourning.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.15, 16.</note> 
                     <hi>The Crown is fallen from our Head: wo unto us that we have ſinned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32727:22"/>
                  <p>Thus let us humble and afflict our Souls before God, who is juſtly diſpleaſed for our manifold Iniquities, and Contempt of his Mercies; and in the midſt of our Sorrows pray we him to remember Mercy: And when we have poured out our Souls, with the bittereſt Grief and Sorrow of Heart for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible Loſs, in ſuch a deep ſenſe as ſo ſad an Occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, let us ſay,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Thou, O Lord, remaineſt for ever, thy Throne from Generation to Generation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Turn thou us unto thee, O Lord, and ſo ſhall we be turned, renew our Days as of old;</hi> renew them, O Lord, and continue them unto us in our Gracious KING <hi>WILLIAM.</hi> And God be praiſed that we Enjoy him, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Religion, our Laws, our Liberties, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. What a Mercy is it that we have His Majeſty ſtill? <hi>In whoſe Preſervation, not only the Welfare of his own Subjects, but of all</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>is ſo nearly concerned.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">See the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of both Houſes to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, <hi>Dec. 31. 1694.</hi>
                     </note>As the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Houſe of Peers, and agreeably thereto the Honourable Commons, have in their great Wiſdom pronounced.</p>
                  <p>Let us then turn from the Evil of our Ways, and lift up our Hands and Hearts to Heaven, that God may be Gracious to us, in granting Him a long and happy Reign over us: And pray we that God will Support and Comfort His Majeſty and Us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Burden of His and <hi>Our Great Loſs,</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">In His Majeſty's Gracious Anſwer to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the Houſe of Peers, <hi>Dec. 31. 1694.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>which</hi> He was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to declare <hi>is above what he can expreſs:</hi> And that he was <hi>able to think of nothing but it.</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Anſwer to the Houſe of Commons Addreſs.</note> So ſharply did his Grief thereupon aſſail and pierce his Royal Heart. Tho' always known to be of ſuch Heroick and Invincible Courage, that nothing could diſmay him; this ſad Affliction alone Conquered him, has been of ſuch weight, as to over-burden and ſink his Spirits; the like to which no Difficulties, no Dangers could ever before effect; not Ten Thouſand Meſſengers of Death flying about him. <hi>Behold how he loved</hi> Her!</p>
                  <p>Pray we then to God to be His Majeſty's Comforter in this great Trial, and to make us all moſt Dutiful and Obedient Subjects unto him, paying him double Homage and Fealty; that we may not once waver in our Fidelity, but multiply in our Hearts Zealous Prayers, and all good Deſires for his Long Life and Proſperity; and then we may expect to Enjoy a large ſhare of Her Late Majeſty in Him: He will not only Defend us as He hath done, but alſo will be unto us in her ſtead, by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32727:22"/>His more abundant Favours to us; if an addition can be made to His former; becauſe Virtue and Goodneſs were conjunctive in Their Majeſties; what One did, was generally the Act of Both. And as they by <hi>Marriage</hi> were <hi>one Fleſh,</hi> ſo they ſeem'd, by an Happy Unity and Concord in every thing, to have one and the ſame Mind, as if they had had but one Soul. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, we may truſt He will take all the Care of us upon himſelf, and be unto us both as KING and QUEEN, to do us all the Good that lies in His Royal Power.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, to conclude, as we mourn for Her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and deſire to Conſecrate her Memory to be for Ever Bleſſed, thus paying our laſt Tribute unto <hi>Her</hi> in Tears: So let us with the higheſt Deference Honour and Obey <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> the Great Patron and Aſſertor of the Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> of <hi>Ours</hi> chiefly: And let us always Pray, <hi>GOD Save KING</hi> WILLIAM. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:23"/>
                  <p>The Living Lord, a Rock of Salvation.</p>
                  <p>SERMON III. Preached in <hi>Mortlake</hi> Church in <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RREY, April</hi> the 16th 1696.</p>
                  <p>Being the Day of a General Thankſgiving for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the KING, from the Intended Aſſaſſination of His Royal Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="3" type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:32727:24"/>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:32727:24"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2 SAM. xxii. 47.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be my Rock: and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THat the Merciful and Gracious Eye of God's Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence hath, in a moſt Signal manner, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over this Nation for good, eſpecially ſince the Bleſſed Reformation, is beyond all poſſibility of Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That he hath been ſundry times, and in divers manners, a Rock of Salvation unto it, by many powerful Deliverances thereof from Evil, is as certain, as if it were a thing proved by Mathematical Demonſtration: To recount, and inlarge upon all which, time would fail me. But for a full Teſtimony unto my Aſſertion, let us look back into the Annals and Hiſtories of Times paſt, but of One Century of Years, and part of another; and by thoſe laſting Monuments of the Dead, let us <hi>ask our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and they will ſhew us, our Elders, and they will tell us,</hi> what great and marvellous Things God did in the Days of Old, for them, and us their Poſterity. They were Eye-witneſſes in times paſt, and Partakers of the Goodneſs of the Lord unto the Sons of Men in this ſinful Land: And are not we in this reſpect, the like to the full in our Generation, as they were in theirs? Or rather, hath not God ſuperadded to us, and made his preſent meaſure of Grace and Favour to overflow amongſt us, by his great Salvation given unto us? Of which, every one who will not cloſe his Eyes, hath ocular and ſenſible demonſtration laid before him in view, in ſuch large and legible Characters, <hi>that he that runs may read it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this we may all read in the Book of our own Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that when our Conſciences were in apparent danger to be Inſlaved with Erroneous Doctrines, Superſtition, and a Falſe Way of Worſhipping God; or elſe our Lives muſt be Sacrificed to the mercileſs Fury of our Implacable Enemies; that when
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32727:25"/>our Laws, our Liberties, and Properties, were to be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by ſuch a Power, as would know no Limits: Then <hi>God, that heareth Prayer,</hi> the Prayer of the Humble and Afflicted, heard our Petitions; and when we could not imagine which way the Salvation ſhould come, or by whom under him it ſhould be effected; then he appeared to be a God, <hi>who judgeth the Earth, and bowed the Heavens, and came down,</hi> ſending to our Aid, with the Arm of Power, and Crowning with Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Succeſs His Preſent Moſt Excellent and Sacred Majeſty, our Moſt Gracious Sovereign, and Rightful Lord, KING <hi>WILLIAM:</hi> For whom all Praiſe, Adoration, and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, which the Finite and Weak Underſtandings, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Mortal Men can give unto an Infinite Being, an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and Omnipotent God, are a Tribute due unto Him.</p>
                  <p>But though God be always Merciful, there are Sons of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> who will be moſt Wicked, will Murmur and Repine, and even Deſpiſe and Croſs the Divine Goodneſs, and will not have Him to Reign over us, whom God hath appointed to be our King, and hath made, next to Himſelf, our Mighty Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer.</p>
                  <p>Againſt whom nevertheleſs, that there ſhould be Men Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Benign Influences of His Merciful and Happy Government, who Conſpire with Gall and Bitterneſs of Spirit, not only to Dethrone Him, but Inſidiouſly and Baſely, in a moſt Barbarous and Inhuman manner to take away His Sacred Life, by the Aſſaſſination and Murder of His Royal Perſon, notwithſtanding all his Clemency; and thereby to make way for a Foreign and Arbitrary Power to ruſh in upon theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the Deſtruction of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Laws, and Liberties. It would ſeem incredible to Men of Reaſon and Ingenuity; be to them more than a Paradox; but that it is no longer in the dark, being now clearly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and (the Good God be Bleſſed and Praiſed therefore) the Miſchief moſt providentially prevented. Wherefore, Sing we every one, with holy <hi>David</hi> in the front of this Divine Canticle,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 2, 3.</note> or Pſalm, <hi>The Lord is my Rock, and my Fortreſs, and my Deliverer: The God of my Rock, in Him will I truſt: He is my Shield, and the Horn of my Salvation, my high Tower, and my Refuge, my Saviour; Thou ſaveſt</hi> thine Anointed and Us <hi>from Violence.</hi> And again join we with the Royal Pſalmiſt in a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32727:25"/>Hope and Confidence in God, in Acclamations of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and Praiſes unto Him; evermore rejoicing and ſaying, <hi>The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be my Rock; and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which words are part of holy <hi>David</hi>'s Song of Deliverance; (this Chapter and the 18th Pſalm being of one and the ſame ſubſtance, but run with a little variation of reading in ſome parts) wherein that great Saint, then but Militant, did Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Solemnities of an holy Triumph and Praiſe, to the God of his Salvation; who had preſerved his Perſon from the great Dangers that had threatned him from the violent Hands of <hi>Saul,</hi> and other his Inveterate Enemies, who had by various Snares and Stratagems ſought his Life; for thus we find the Preface, or Inſcription to this Thankſgiving Hymn of the ſweet <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> of <hi>Iſrael. And</hi> David <hi>ſpake unto the Lord the words of this Song, in the Day that the Lord had delivered him out of the Hand of all his Enemies, and out of the Hand of</hi> Saul.</p>
                  <p>And with ſuch a lofty ſtrain of Melody and delightful Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony has he run through this his Noble <hi>Anthem,</hi> as muſt needs Charm his chief Muſician, both in ſetting and playing the Tune proper to it. And alſo with a Raviſhing Delight raiſe and exhilarate the Spirits of the whole <hi>Choir;</hi> thoſe concern'd therein, either with Vocal or Inſtrumental Muſick; thoſe that ſang, or thoſe that play'd on the Organ, Harp, or Cymbal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chearing and refreſhing even the Hearts and Souls of all then preſent.</p>
                  <p>And moſt grateful are his Acknowledgments of God's Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Benefits unto him, flowing from many of his Holy and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Attributes; from his Free and Immenſe Goodneſs and Mercy, his Incomprehenſible Wiſdom, Infinite Juſtice and Power, and that great Providence, which attended him through ſo many various Scenes of Troubles, in the moſt difficult Stages of his Life.</p>
                  <p>Very expreſſive alſo is he of the Senſe he had of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers he eſcaped: Such like as thoſe out of which God (Bleſſed be his Holy Name for it) lately deliver'd our Moſt Gracious King, even <hi>the Waves and Snares of Death,</hi> the Floods of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men, their deep and ſubtil Plots and Conſpiracies, their violent Stratagems and Devices, as unavoidable as Floods and Inundations of Water are, till God puts a ſtop to them by his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32727:26"/>Omnipotent Command, Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When after ſuch a wondrous and ſpecial manner he is pleaſed to be preſent; as holy <hi>David</hi> hath ſet him forth with the higheſt flights of Divine Rhetorick, uſing many exalted Metaphors to expreſs the ſame; as, of the <hi>Earth trembling</hi> and <hi>ſhaking,</hi> as alſo <hi>the Foundations of Heaven</hi> it ſelf being put into the like terrible <hi>Commotions,</hi> with ſuch <hi>Thunders</hi> and <hi>Lightnings, Storms</hi> and <hi>Tempeſts</hi> of his <hi>Wrath,</hi> as aforetime had really de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd the Enemies of his People.</p>
                  <p>And then, after many Bleſſed Eulogies, and Seraphical Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Holy and Eloquent Dictates from that Spirit, which taught him how to pray unto, as well as to praiſe his Mighty Deliverer; he cloſes the whole Encomium, with glorying in the God of his Salvation, and yet further Returns of Bleſſing and Thankſgiving to him; part whereof the Text doth eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally denote unto us. <hi>The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be my Rock: and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Interpretation and Explanation of which, and for our preſent Edification (on this Day of a General Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughout this Nation for His Majeſty's Bleſſed Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and our Happineſs thereby) I ſhall obſerve theſe Two following Particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, Holy <hi>David</hi>'s Joyful and Triumphant Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God and his Providence, in the former words, <hi>The Lord liveth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, His grateful Return to God of Benediction and Praiſe, or Exaltation, for his Wondrous and Powerful Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of him from the Miſchiefs formed againſt him, Emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally expreſſed in the following parts of the Text, —<hi>and bleſſed be my Rock; and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, <hi>The Lord liveth,</hi> is a Recognition of God and His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, even with an Extaſie of Joy. The Royal Saint being Tranſported thereby into Triumphant Acclamations, in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of God's Potent Deliverances, and Manifold Benefits, through abundance of various and critical Circumſtances of his Race under the Sun, frequently reſcuing him out of the very Jaws of Deſtruction, as they were ready to tear him in pieces;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32727:26"/>as from <hi>Saul</hi>'s Javelin at one time; his and other wicked Mens Inſtigations, their Combining Plots, and Snates, and Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies to ſnatch away his Life, at other times. For all which he might with great Reaſon pronounce, <hi>The Lord liveth.</hi> As for Deliverances from great and apparent Dangers, eſpecially from the intended Miſchief of Bitter Enemies, it is very proper for Men to expreſs their grateful Sentiments in theſe, or words of like conſonance and import: There is a God; a God that Ruleth all; a God that helpeth in time of need; yea, and when we are Poor, and Naked, Blind, and Lame, that without him we ſhould be remedileſs, being our ſelves neither able to ſee the approaching Deſtruction, nor to ward off the Blow, if we have time to ſee it. But the Comfort of all is, <hi>The Lord liveth,</hi> who ſeeth what we cannot ſo much as think of, and ſaves us, when we are ignorant of our Danger, and of our Help and Salvation, ready at the ſame time, the one to devour, and the other to reſcue and protect us Wherefore again, and again, we will with great Joy ſay, <hi>The Lord liveth:</hi> Or, <hi>Let the Lord live,</hi> if any will have it Tranſlated ſo, in way of Triumph al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. As the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were wont to expreſs their Joy and good Wiſhes for their Kings, <hi>Let the King live;</hi> which we turning into an Angliciſm, or form of Speech agreeable to our own Idiom and Language, do expreſs by ſaying, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> and ſo we have Tranſlated it in ſeveral parts of Scripture; as that, <hi>God ſave King</hi> Solomon, at his Inauguration, when he was Anointed King.</p>
                  <p>Which, both in the Hebraiſm, and our Mode or Way of ſpeaking, implies Zeal, and a joyful Acclamation of Triumph and Delight, for the King, and alſo a Prayer for his Life: in which laſt ſence it is improper to Tranſlate this part of the Text, <hi>Let the Lord live,</hi> but not ſo in the former; for with an holy Zeal, and Joy, and Triumph, Delight and Pleaſure, for his Gracious Goodneſs, it may, without any Soleciſm, be ſaid, <hi>Let the Lord live,</hi> as well as, <hi>Let God ariſe, Pſal.</hi> 68.1. that is, Let the Lord appear and manifeſt himſelf to the World, that He is the only Living God, the Almighty and Merciful <hi>Joho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> in ſaving his own People, by putting his <hi>Hook into</hi> the Noſes, <hi>and</hi> his <hi>Bridle into</hi> the <hi>Lips</hi> of their Enemies, and thus checking their malignant Rage and Fury.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:32727:27"/>
                  <p>But to return, as we have moſt fitly render'd it, <hi>The Lord liveth,</hi> we may farther take this weighty Clauſe to have been directed by holy <hi>David</hi>'s Eye againſt a ſet of Ungodly and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical Men; againſt ſuch, as was the Patron of all Fools, <hi>the Fool</hi> that <hi>ſaid in his Heart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1.</note> 
                     <hi>there is no God;</hi> a Fool's ſaying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for who but a Fool would ever have ſaid ſo? And therefore they thought it impoſſible their Devices ſhould prove Abortive; for if there had been no God, by his Omniſcience and Providence to diſcloſe their Secret Cabals, and the Arrows of Death prepared by them to let fly againſt the Lord's Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the ſtroke would have been unavoidable, and fatal; for it is not in Man to diſcover the Secrets of the Hearts of other Men: It is a peculiar Prerogative of the Great Searcher of Hearts to do it, who knows the Thoughts thereof long before their Conception. What a miſerable Condition then had holy <hi>David</hi> been involved in, amidſt all his Enemies Plotting and Deviſing his Ruin, if there had been no God? He muſt then have fallen into their Pit.</p>
                  <p>Well then might he Joy in the God of his Salvation, and Congratulate his own Safety, with theſe words, expreſſing his Aſſurance of Omnipotency on his ſide againſt his Enemies, to their Confuſion, <hi>The Lord liveth;</hi> baffling all hereby, who in his Days denied the Omnipotent Being, or lived and acted as if there were none.</p>
                  <p>And the words have the ſame force againſt the Atheiſts and Wicked Men of our Times, who deny the Exiſtence of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or elſe, ſurely, never have him in their Thoughts; but Plot on, and imagine Vain Things, in their ungodly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, until they fall into the Pit, which they make for the Lord's Anointed, and for the Deſtruction of his People.</p>
                  <p>But further, this Clauſe ſeems alſo to be levell'd againſt a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſort of Fools, who, it's true, might have ſuch a Grain of true Faith, as to make a Confeſſion of the Godhead, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived falſe Articles into their Creed, in reſpect of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Government; as that having his Throne ſo high in the Heavens, he would not humble himſelf to behold the things done on the Earth, and ſo never took any Care of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary Affairs, neither of ſetting up, or pulling down, of right, nor wrong, of oppreſſion, or injuſtice, or any <hi>ſore evil under the San:</hi> So that wicked Men might live in Robbery, Spoil,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32727:27"/>and Oppreſſion, committing Outrage and Violence, and brave it along, ſaying, <hi>Who is Lord over us?</hi> And ſpurning at Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſay, <hi>Tuſh! How ſhould God perceive it? Is there Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Moſt High?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And how ſhall we think better Principles have governed or influenced thoſe amongſt us, who ſo lately meditated upon Regicide, Rebellion, Invaſion, and a Total Subverſion of theſe Three Kingdoms; beſides all the Evil Conſequences, that would neceſſarily, like a mighty Deluge, have flowed in upon many other Nations and People: For their Barbarous Practices ſeem to be the Interpreters of their Minds; ſo that if any will deny the Hypotheſis, that they were ſuch; the ſequel drawn from their Bitter Deſigns infers a Concluſion, proving as much againſt them in deed and reality; let them plead for their Thoughts, and their Faith or Belief, as they pleaſe; at moſt their Arguments can be of no force on their ſide, any otherwiſe than thoſe of Rank Practical Atheiſts are againſt them we call ſpeculative: And certainly they are the worſt of Men, who profeſs to believe well, and practice moſt ill; and ſuch juſtly incur the Divine Abhorrence, are frequently forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God, being Veſſels of his Wrath, and left alone to themſelves, working out their own Deſtruction. That <hi>burden of the Lord</hi> in the 23d Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> v. 33. being their Portion, <hi>I will even forſake you ſaith the Lord;</hi> with that direful Cataſtrophe, as an Appendix to the Curſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd in the end of the Chapter, <hi>And I will bring an Everlaſting Reproach upon you, and a perpetual ſhame, which ſhall not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> This was to be the Fate of ſome Prophets, and Prieſts, with the People, who were untoward, and diſſatisfied with God's Ways in thoſe Days. And let them, who find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alike grieved in our Age, make Application hereof to themſelves; whilſt we, who are ſenſible of God's great and undeſerved Bleſſings to us, in our Moſt Gracious King, and this Deliverance, and are thankful for them, will ſing <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi> unto His Infinite Holineſs; and with Glory, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, expreſs the gladneſs of our Souls, in ſaying every one of us with the Royal Pſalmiſt, <hi>The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be my Rock, and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation.</hi> Which introduces the</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:32727:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Second Propoſition, comprehending King <hi>David</hi>'s grateful Return to God of Benediction, and Praiſe, or Exaltation, for his Marvellous and Powerful Deliverances of him from the Miſchieſs formed againſt him, Emphatically expreſſed in theſe words, —<hi>and bleſſed be my Rock: and exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Agreeable to the Dutiful and Pious Cuſtom of God's Church in all Ages, of bleſſing and praiſing Him, for His particular Providence, in great Deliverances, (beſides the Acts of His Univerſal Goodneſs) is this Hymn of holy <hi>David.</hi> And of the whole Compoſure, theſe words laſt recited have a ſound, which ſeems the moſt Harmonious, becauſe they rebound with ſo pleaſant an Echo, as is enough to refreſh a Devout and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul, meditating upon the Mercies of God.</p>
                  <p>So that an Excellent Pattern of a great Solemnity in this kind we have here; and many more there are in the holy Records of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church:<note place="margin">Exod <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> Such is the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the Overthrow of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt in the Red Sea, and their own ſafe paſſage through the ſame, from their hard Servitude and Bondage in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Such is the Song of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jude <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> for their great Victory over <hi>Siſera, Captain</hi> or General <hi>of the Hoſt of</hi> Jabin <hi>King of</hi> Canaan; and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>'s Deliverance from his Maſter's Oppreſſion. Such is the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of King <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>'s and his People's Praiſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.</note> and Joy, and Triumph, for a mighty Victory over, and Salvation from, a numerous Heatheniſh Hoſt; beſides many others, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Obſervation. When Godly Princes and Rulers have excited themſelves and their People to be thankful, as our Moſt Gracious King has commanded us now to be; as His Royal Anceſtors, and many other Kings and Potentates have, upon the like Occaſions, ſent out their Mandates and Decrees, requiring their People to <hi>give Glory</hi> and Praiſe unto the God of their Salvation. And a good Principle it is of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> readily to obey, from time to time, the <hi>Defenders</hi> of Her <hi>Faith,</hi> in commanding that, which ſhe owns an Indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Duty and Tribute to the King of Kings; from which may not any of her Members ſwerve at this time! But may every one with joint conſent heartily ſay <hi>Amen</hi> this Day to theſe words, —<hi>bleſſed be my Rock: and exalted be the God of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32727:28"/>Rock of my Salvation,</hi> and that upon the account of our preſent Grounds for Thankſgiving!</p>
                  <p>Which Metaphor of a <hi>Rock</hi> is of frequent uſe in Holy Writ, and hath divers ſignifications: So that this thankful Expreſſion, —<hi>bleſſed be my Rock,</hi> carries the ſence and authority of, Bleſſed be my ſure and immoveable Foundation: Bleſſed be my Help and mighty Defence: Bleſſed be my Refuge and Salvation: And ſo Bleſſed be my God Himſelf, who is all theſe to His Faithful Servants. As (to illuſtrate this by other Examples) he is alſo an Horn, and Tower, or Fortreſs of Salvation unto them: For a Horn denotes Glory and Strength, great Power and Might, all which are Infinite in Him: And a Tower is the Emblem of Succour and Safeguard, and, as ſuch, well applied unto God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous runneth into it, and is ſafe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore holy <hi>David</hi> aptly reſembles God to a Rock: For what in Nature is ſtronger than a Rock? And therefore what could be a more proper Hieroglyphick than it, to expreſs God in His Attribute of Omnipotency, by which He is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver His Servants, when void of all Hope; and who is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above Nature, but infinitely tranſcends all other Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Beings, whether they be Thrones, Principalities, Powers, or any other Order and Degree, of the whole Celeſtial Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>And whereas it follows in the Text, —<hi>exalted be the God of the Rock of my Salvation:</hi> The meaning is obvious and eaſie, with this Comment or Gloſs unto it, naturally drawn from the aforeſaid Interpretation of the Trope, by which the Lord is likened to a Rock; for by it this Clauſe doth aſcribe Exaltation and Praiſe to the God ſtrong and able to ſave. As if the Royal Prophet had magnified him thus; exalted or praiſed be the God of the Strength, or of the Power of my Salvation, by whoſe irreſiſtible Might I was preſerved from the Violence of my Cruel Enemies. Not that Man can add any thing to God in all this, whereby to make Him greater, in any reſpect, than He is in Himſelf; but it is by way of an humble and thankful Declaration of His Glory, His Greatneſs, His Immenſe Power, and Goodneſs. It is a <hi>telling out</hi> of <hi>His Praiſe, and Wondrous Acts;</hi> a <hi>ſhewing forth the Mercy and Loving-kindneſs of the Lord,</hi> with Gratitude and Joy: When Men are not hardned againſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32727:29"/>Mercy, but are ſenſible that they have ſeen and taſted the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant Goodneſs of the Lord, after His Countenance hath, of His Free Grace, ſhined with unſpeakable Favour upon them.</p>
                  <p>And now,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Give ear, O ye Heavens, and I will ſpeak; and hear, O Earth, the words of my Mouth.</hi> For <hi>I will publiſh</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things, that <hi>the Lord hath done for us:</hi> And I will <hi>aſcribe</hi> the Glory and <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of all unto <hi>our God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For, <hi>many and great are the wondrous Works, which the Lord our God hath done, like as be alſo his Thoughts, which are to us-ward; O how great is the Sum of them! Who can reckon them up in order to Him? If I ſhould declare them, and ſpeak of them; they ſhould be more than I am able to expreſs.</hi> Wherefore I ſhall not pretend to enumerate and publiſh the whole Series and Catalogue of His Mercies, from time to time conferred upon us; for, if I could bring them all within the reach of my Diſcourſe, which is next to impoſſibility; yet my preſent Task does not oblige me to run through ſo large a Province, but more eſpecially binds me to the Buſineſs of this Day; of the Great and Auſpicious Deliverance, for which we Celebrate the Solemnity of a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Thankſgiving, for God's late unſpeakable Mercies to the King, and theſe Realms. And therefore we will in ſilence admire His Marvellous Preſervations that are paſt, and employ our Thoughts on his preſent Salvation. We will only think how Famous the Two laſt <hi>Eighty Eights</hi> are: The former by a Succeſsful Deliverance of this Nation from the threatned De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, when her Enemies ſent againſt it their <hi>Invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mada,</hi> as they then in the height of Pride and Oſtentation na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, and which periſhed with Shame and Confuſion: And the laſt <hi>Eighty Eight</hi> is Glorious for our Memorable and Bleſſed Preſervation from Apparent Dangers at Home, from Evil and Deſtruction growing up in the midſt of us; the Flames of which were quenched, and the Rage and Fury ſtopt, by the moſt Happy Coming of our Good and Gracious KING <hi>WILLIAM</hi> to our Relief, making thereby another <hi>Fifth</hi> Day of <hi>November</hi> as great an Enſign of God's ſpecial Providence to us, as that <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>November</hi> ſtill is by the Diſcovery of that Horrid, that moſt Trayterous and Bloody-intended Maſſacre by Gunpowder. Theſe things let us think on <hi>with the Praiſes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32727:29"/>of God in our Mouths,</hi> and with all Humility, Devotion, and Gratitude in our Hearts.</p>
                  <p>And for His unſpeakable Goodneſs, for which we Solemnize this Day, ſet apart by Royal Authority for the Holy Exerciſe of Praiſe and Adoration unto the Supreme Governour of the Univerſe, from whom cometh Salvation at all times; let us believe in the Lord, with Joy and Thankſgiving; and Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly ſay, That <hi>the Lord liveth;</hi> that He ſeeth and ordereth all things; that his Preſence fills all places, and his Providence is buſie and active every where; that He hath done <hi>great things for us, whereof we rejoice.</hi> And this affirm we in defiance of all, who deny Him, or his Providence, whether in Thought, or in Act, or be it by both. And for all this may we fear Him; may we love Him above all things in Heaven and in Earth: May all our Hearts, all our Souls, our Minds, and our Strength, have a full ſhare in this Affection towards God; and ſo by the Operation of every Faculty and Power in us proper thereto, may we take our fill in loving Him; that as He hath loved us, ſo the love of <hi>Him may dwell plenteouſly in us!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To excite us the more to our Duty of Love, and Praiſe, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, and Thankſgiving, it is requiſite that we conſider what and how great the Bleſſing is; wherein conſiſts the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation wrought ſo lately in our Land.</p>
                  <p>And of the Bleſſing of God now upon us, and His Salvation vouchſafed unto us, none can be ignorant; foraſmuch as all know, that God Almighty has manifeſted his Providence, his Power, and Mercy towards His Moſt Excellent Majeſty, and His People, by laying open the Depths of Satan, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intentions of wicked Men; that He has Diſcovered, and Delivered the King from an Horrid and Barbarous Conſpiracy of Papiſts, and other Trayterous Perſons, to Aſſaſſinate and Murder His Royal Perſon; and the Kingdom from an Intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Invaſion by the greateſt Enemies to its and all <hi>Europe</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the <hi>French.</hi> By which great Deliverance, the King's Royal Perſon is ſaved from Deſtruction, His Government Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, and this Realm Freed from that Total Subverſion of its Religion, Laws, and Liberties; which, if God had not thus mercifully interpoſed, would have been the Fate of it.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:32727:30"/>
                  <p>Lo! this is the Bleſſing, and it is very great; this is the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation we now give thanks for, and it is wonderful. Here is repeated Mercy and Goodneſs, to an unwiſe and fooliſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who have ill requited God with Ingratitude for His former Loving-kindneſſes.</p>
                  <p>But as we now meditate on His Mercy; ſo may we, with Rivers of Tears in our Eyes, think of the other Method, God ſo lately uſed to reduce us unto a right Senſe of our ſelves; by the Deplorable Loſs of that moſt Virtuous and Pious Princeſs, the Queen of Bleſſed Memory; who fell by a heavy ſtroke, alas! To us it was; God puniſhing us for our many Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, our Incorrigible and Undutiful Behaviour to Him, that He might melt us thereby into Sorrow and Repentance; that He might force us to humble our ſelves with Weeping and Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to cloath our Souls with Mourning Attire, when the thick Cloud of his Anger overſpread theſe Nations, by Her Death.</p>
                  <p>And now again He invites us to Him in love; for, lo! the Bright Beams of His Mercy ſhining every where. He hath called us this Day out of the Houſes of Mourning, into thoſe of Joy. <hi>He hath put a new Song into our Mouths, even a Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving unto our God,</hi> for the Safety of our Moſt Serene and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Monarch, KING <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> the Father of our Country; the Great Joy, and Hope, and Support of many Nations; the moſt Heroick and Noble Patron and Aſſertor of ours, and all <hi>Europe</hi>'s Liberties; by whoſe Crown falling from His Head, and ſo <hi>the Glory</hi> departing again <hi>from</hi> us, God might have laid us with Bleeding Hearts in Duſt and Aſhes; have heaped upon us all the Miſchiefs, that the Rage and Madneſs of our Incenſed Enemies could bring; who would have num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd their Merits by the quantities of our Blood, they ſhould have cauſed to run in our Streets; when the more of us they had killed, the more Service to God they would have boaſted that they had done; like that Duke <hi>D'Alva,</hi> who aſſumed much Glory and Honour to himſelf, for the Slaughter he made of many Thouſand Proteſtants, or Hereticks, by ſuch Men of Blood, falſly ſo called.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:32727:30"/>
                  <p>But, <hi>O that Men would praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Wonders he doeth for us the Children of Men,</hi> when by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Mercy we are ſaved from that Wo and Deſtruction, which otherwiſe would at this time have been raging by Fire and Sword in theſe Iſlands; with Apparent Danger of Ruin and Deſolation upon all the Confederate Countries, by that Ambitious Prince, who has hunted after the Precious Life of our KING, that he might Subdue the Nations to the Rod of his Power, and tread them under his Feet. But behold the Juſtice of the Lord, as well as his Mercy, in the King's Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For what had Men to do to take God's Prerogative out of His Hands, and to number the King's Moments of Life, by the time they ſhould ſet a Fatal period thereto. So long as God hath bound up his Soul in the Bundle of Life (and may it be, I pray God, for many Years, even to a good Old Age) thoſe who have to do with <hi>the Stool of Wickedneſs,</hi> may ſit thereon long enough, Plotting and Contriving his Death; thus <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> or framing <hi>Miſchief,</hi> by their own Wicked Counſels, <hi>as a Law</hi> or Decree, written like, but more Cruel than thoſe of <hi>Draco</hi> ſaid to be in Blood, and yet ſhall not be able to prevail, with all the Powers of Hell on their ſide: For no Sorcery, no Divination, no Inchantment, no Conſpiracy, or Weapon form'd againſt this Mighty Defender of our Faith, and of the Liberties of <hi>Europe</hi> can proſper, ſo long as the Lord is on our ſide; ſo long as He is the Rock of our Salvation; and He will not <hi>leave us, nor forſake us,</hi> if we do not leave Him firſt. O therefore draw we near unto Him in Faith and full Aſſurance of His continual Favour, and keep we from every wicked thing; from Atheiſm of the Mind, from Atheiſm of the Will, and the Act: From Profaneneſs in our Hearts, in our Words, and in our Deeds! Let us Religiouſly obſerve this Day with an holy Joy, that it may be acceptable unto the Lord. Let no vain Oaths cauſe the Land to mourn; nor any other Sin of our Souls or Bodies pollute this Day. And let us obſerve every Lord's Day with greater diſtinction from other Days, than we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to done. And ſo may we now turn unto the Lord, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. May we waſh off all Stains and Blemiſhes of paſt Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and be thankful for evermore hereafter.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:32727:31"/>
                  <p>And then will we ſay unto the Grand Enemy of <hi>Europe, The Virgin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.22.</note> 
                     <hi>the Daughter of</hi> Zion, <hi>hath deſpiſed thee, and laughed thee to ſcorn, the Daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>hath ſhaken her Head at thee.</hi> Then the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for her Faith is Built on a Rock, and He, who is truly the Defender thereof, ſhall ſtand by Her, with Power from God, to preſerve Her, as He hath promiſed to do, to His utmoſt.</p>
                  <p>To our Conſolation then be it ſpoken, That <hi>Great Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance giveth God unto His King; that he is a Tower of Salvation unto him, and ſheweth Mercy unto His Anointed.</hi> Wherefore will we rejoice and ſing triumphantly, <hi>The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be</hi> our <hi>Rock, and exalted be the god of the Rock of</hi> our <hi>Salvation.</hi> We will magnifie His Name, by declaring what He hath done for us. We will truſt upon Him that He will <hi>grant the King a Long Life, and not deny Him the Requeſt of his Lips,</hi> but that he will <hi>give Him His Heart's Deſire,</hi> the firm Settlement of our Church and State, and the Peace and Tranquility of <hi>Europe.</hi> To this end we will pray, That God will keep Him from every Evil Man, and preſerve Him from all thoſe Wicked and Violent Men, who lay Snares for Him: That <hi>He</hi> will <hi>ſet</hi> His <hi>Feet upon a Rock, and eſtabliſh</hi> His <hi>Goings.</hi> And then, <hi>unto thee, O God,</hi> will <hi>we give Thanks, unto thee</hi> will <hi>we give thanks;</hi> as we do this Day, for ſmiting the Hearts of ſome of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, forcing them thereby to diſcloſe the wicked Devices of Ungodly Men, to bring the moſt Secret Deeds of Darkneſs to Light, and prevent the Execrable Attempt.</p>
                  <p>And Bleſſed be thy holy Name, O Lord, for giving the Auguſt and moſt Honourable Senate of this Land a true Sence of the Danger, we have eſcaped; Wiſdom to conſult for the King's Safety, the Welfare and Happineſs of theſe Iſlands, and the Utility and Repoſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> with Brave and Heroick Courage, and Reſolution to knit together as one Man, for the Defence of the KING, and Support of His Government. And Bleſſed be God, the generality of theſe Kingdoms, ſuch vaſt numbers of Men of all Orders and Degrees, States and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do follow their Example, in ſhewing their Reſentments and Abhorrence of the Helliſh and Villanous Deſign, and in Aſſociating for the Defence of the King, and His People;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32727:31"/>which let us all do with our Hearts, as well as our Hands; and ſo have the Honour of Aſſociating with the King Himſelf, and His Parliament, with Foreign Princes and Potentates, as well as with the numerous Armies of our Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
                  <p>And the more to ſtir us up to our Duty, obſerve we farther the Abhorrence and Deteſtation, with which Foreign Princes, States, and People, expreſs themſelves in this matter: How they rejoice at the Happy Diſcovery; for which (we hear) ſome ſing the <hi>Te Deum;</hi> ſome appoint publick Thankſgivings in their Churches throughout their Dominions; and others give ample Proof unto the World, that their Souls rejoice at the King's Deliverance. And <hi>Bleſſed of God be</hi> all that are thankful, and do rejoice for His unſpeakable Mercies, whether they be the King's Subjects at Home, or His Friends, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies Abroad.</p>
                  <p>Now, as it highly Concerns all to be thankful; ſo likewiſe to turn from the evil of their Ways, that the Lord may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his watchful Providence over them; and either melt the Hearts of the Stubborn and Rebellious into Softneſs, into Quiet and Peaceable Tempers; or elſe, if they continue Obdurate, and Miſchievous in their Principles, that He will Infatuate their Counſels, and Defeat their Malignant Purpoſes, that they may not <hi>quench the light of</hi> our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To raiſe our Thoughts then unto a juſt Exerciſe of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; let us conſider how Black and Extenſive the Cloud lately hanging over our Heads was; how general and fierce the Storm would have been, if it had fallen upon us by the King's Death, and a ſudden Invaſion from <hi>France.</hi> We know not what would have become of us by this time, how we ſhould have rolled in Blood e're this; whether any diſtinction of Age or Sex, Order or Degree, would have deliver'd any from wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in Blood. It is likely, High and Low, Young and Old, the Mother and her Sucking-Infant, ſhould have equally ſuffered in the Common Calamity. Some, perhaps, who can make Shipwrack of their Faith, would have flatter'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Vain Hopes of their Airy Imaginations, that the Mountains of Idle Thoughts, heaped up confuſedly in their Heads, ſhould have brought forth Wonderful Matters, a Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32727:32"/>and Bleſſed Off-ſpring; whereas the Birth would have made them ſo Ridiculous, as to Merit Shame and Hiſſing, and as Miſerable, as they were fond of their <hi>Babel,</hi> by which they would mount on high, and get a Name: And a Name they have gotten, but 'tis of Shame and Reproach; 'tis a Name that ſtinks; 'tis one that ſhall rot, and their Memorial ſhall periſh with them, or elſe a Curſe and Infamy will attend both, if they are not forgotten.</p>
                  <p>But why ſo Bloody and Baſe, as to Aſſaſſinate His Moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty? Is Regicide become no Sin? Is the Murder of a Great Prince Meritorious at laſt? And that by way-laying Him, to Circumvent and Trappan Him out of His Life: O horrid Crime! But know ye wretched Souls, and Blood-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Spirits, and know it to your Terror and Confuſion, that our KING is ready often enough to preſent Himſelf in Battel-Array to His Enemies, if they would accept of a Challenge. But they know His Valour and Conduct too well, to venture upon that, which is wont to Coſt them ſo Dear, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm Receptions for ſuch their Cowardize and Fear, which have Betray'd them to Unnatural and Savage Methods; for which may Shame and Reproach cleave unto them, as the <hi>Leproſie</hi> of <hi>Naaman</hi> did upon <hi>Gehazi</hi> for his Lie,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.</note> and Prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For wicked Men they are: <hi>Instruments of Cruelty, Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of Violence are in their Habitations. O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5, 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>unto their Aſſembly mine Honour be thou not united. Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce, and their Wrath, for it was cruel.</hi> May God <hi>divide them in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſcatter</hi> them <hi>in</hi> Iſrael, that Confuſion may cover them; and may their Practices be abhorr'd of all Men.</p>
                  <p>But now further, what a Change of Religion ſhould we have had, with a fiery Trial to bear Witneſs unto it? And as for Laws, what help could we have expected from them, when the Sword ſhould have ſupplied their room, and ſuperſeded their Authority? And as for Liberty, they would have taken all that from us, and aſſumed it to themſelves, that they might have done with us as they had pleaſed. And as for Property, that ſhould have vaniſhed with our other Felicities, or elſe have been transferr'd wholly to them, for nothing muſt we have called ours, when all ſhould have been in their Poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:32727:32"/>
                  <p>And how ſtrangely would the Face of Affairs Abroad have been changed for the worſe, to all <hi>Europe?</hi> How would the Edge of the now Victorious Sword of all the Confederate Princes have been turned, and blunted? How would the Two Great Enemies of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> the <hi>Gallick</hi> and <hi>Mahometan,</hi> have Triumphed, and with all Fury imaginable ſet upon the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof? When they would not have been aware of the Blow, until it had put them into much Conſternation and Diſorder. And it would have been Sad and Lamentable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if the Stroke ſhould have forced them (as too ſoon it might) to ſubmit unto the Inglorious and Servile Terms, which Two ſuch Ambitious and Cruel Enemies ſhould have impoſed upon them; if any thing would have contented them, beſides abſolnte Conqueſt, Will, and Pleaſure. O, therefore, great is the Deliverance, beyond the Comprehenſions of our Underſtandings. And <hi>praiſed be the Lord, who hath not given us over for a prey unto their Teeth,</hi> for <hi>our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler: the Snare is broken, and we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For which may all, that are, or would have been ſenſible of the Black Device, if it had taken its Diſmal Effect, Bleſs and Exalt God's holy Name. May all the good People of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Obey their Sovereign Lord the KING's Commands in ſuch manner as may be acceptable to God. And as His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty doth, ſo may they acknowledge the <hi>ſingular Mercy and Goodneſs of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See His Majeſty's Moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Speech to Both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Feb. 24. 1695.</hi>
                     </note> May all His Subjects Piouſly and Joyfully keep this Day, and ponder the Occaſion of it in their Hearts, with a Perpetual Thankſgiving to the utmoſt extent of their Lives, for ſo great a Salvation. May it make ſuch deep and laſting Impreſſions in their Souls. Yea, let them tell it to their Childrens Children, that the Generations to come may Bleſs God for it. And may no Rank, or Quality, Sex, Order, or Degree, think themſelves exempted from their Duty on this Day, which the KING, with the Advice of his Nobles, hath thought fit to apply to ſo Solemn and Sacred a Uſe: But <hi>praiſe the Lord, ye Houſe of</hi> our <hi>Iſrael; praiſe the Lord, ye Houſe of</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron; <hi>praiſe the Lord ye Houſe of</hi> Levi; ye Clergy of this Land: <hi>Ye that fear the Lord, praiſe the Lord, and confeſs he is Gracious, and his Mercy endureth for ever. Kings of the Earth, and all People,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32727:33"/>Princes, and all Judges of the World. Young Men and Maidens, Old Men and Children, praiſe the Name of the Lord: for his Name only is Excellent, and his Praiſe above Heaven and Earth. He ſhall exalt the Horn of his People, all his Saints ſhall praiſe him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now pray we unto God to open Mens Eyes, that they may ſee, and <hi>know thoſe things that belong unto their Peace;</hi> that they may not be Credulous of Dreams and Fancies, nor give heed unto Fables: As if that Monarch, who has Troubled <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> a long time, has Cruelly Perſecuted and Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Proteſtants, and has laid waſte Defenced Cities into Rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous heaps; as if he would ſhew all Clemency and Kindneſs to us; as if he would make every one Happy and Great, with large Donatives of Riches and Honour, Fields and Vineyards, and all the Delights of the Sons of Men; which to think is very incongruous to Reaſon, and diſſonant to the Sentiments of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prudence; unleſs he, and all his Admirers and Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites loved the People of this Nation better than they do; and except we would abandon our Religion; which may we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as think of doing, nor fear his Menaces, or any high and lofty Looks.</p>
                  <p>But keep we ſtedfaſt to our God, and our Faith; to our Duty and Allegiance unto our Sovereign Lord the KING's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; to our Laws, our Liberties, and our Country, and to one another, in Love and Unity. And may god ſhower down His Bleſſings upon us, and make His great Salvation, for which we now offer unto Him the Sacrifice of Thankſgiving, a Pledge of more His abundant Favours to His Anointed, and His Subjects. And let us always therefore have ſomewhat of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Holy Song or Eulogy in our Mouths: Plenteouſly may we be furniſhed in the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Children of Iſrael;</hi> of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak;</hi> and in that great Magazine of Praiſes and Benedictions, <hi>the Book of Pſalms,</hi> together with many other places of the Sacred Canon of Scripture. Let us often think of God's Mercies to us, and make Melody in our Hearts unto Him, with ſuch Excellent and Proper Leſſons, as may be taken out of thoſe Breathings of the Holy Ghoſt. Let <hi>Lute and Harp awake, and</hi> let us <hi>awake right early,</hi> with <hi>the high Praiſes of God in</hi> our <hi>Mouth.</hi> Let this be the Badge of our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Gratitude, <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi> Let us bind it as Signs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32727:33"/>upon our Hands, and Frontlets between our Eyes; together with the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> the <hi>Benedictus,</hi> the <hi>Magnificat;</hi> and like Joyous and Devout Trophies of God's Salvation. Evermore with the Choir of Saints and Angels above, Chanting forth the <hi>Triſhagion, Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Sabaoth, Heaven and Earth are full of the Majeſty of thy Glory. Glory be to thee, O Lord Moſt High.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, As we praiſe God this Day for His Admired Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſo let us Beg His Continuance of it to us, and pray heartily that the now enſuing Campaign may be Victorious, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ance,</hi> and the <hi>Ottoman Empire;</hi> and that an Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Laſting Peace to <hi>England,</hi> and Her <hi>Allies</hi> and Friends, may ſucceed thereupon; and that God will be pleaſed to Bleſs with <hi>Length of Days, and Riches and Honour</hi> in His Throne here, and to Crown afterwards, with <hi>a far more exceeding, and Eternal Weight of Glory</hi> in the higheſt Heavens, His Anointed Servant, our Dread Sovereign Lord, and Lawful and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful KING <hi>WILLIAM. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
